<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A model of private prayers or, occasional helps in retired devotions. / Composed by Edward Wolley, D.D. chaplain in ordinary to his Majesty.</title>
            <author>Wolley, Edward, 1603-1684.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 178 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 102 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96807</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3264</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E2130_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208322</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208715</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867643</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867643</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119587</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96807)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119587)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 243:E2130[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A model of private prayers or, occasional helps in retired devotions. / Composed by Edward Wolley, D.D. chaplain in ordinary to his Majesty.</title>
                  <author>Wolley, Edward, 1603-1684.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 69, [5] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.R. and are to be sold by William Palmer, at the sign of the Palm-tree in Fleet-street, and at the Gun in St. Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>First word of title in Greek characters.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Bound following: The parents blessing their children, and the children begging (on their knees) their parents blessings... .</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prayers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:119587:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:119587:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>'ΕΥΛΟΓΙΑ.</p>
                  <p>The Parents bleſſing their Children: And the Children begging (on their Knees) their Parents BLESSINGS, Are pious Actions, warrantable by the Word of God, and practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed by Gods Saints and Servants.</p>
                  <p>With a Model of private Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, or occaſional Helps in retired De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions.</p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Legibus Comparatum eſt; ut Charitas li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berorum Parentes Amiciores redderet Reipublicae,</hi> 
                     <bibl>M.T. Cicero <hi>ad Brutum.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
                  <p>By Ed. WOLLEY, D.D. and Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain in ordinary to His Majeſtie.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed ly <hi>T. R.</hi> for <hi>William Palmer,</hi> at the ſign of the <hi>Palm-tree</hi> in <hi>Fleetſtreet,</hi> 1661</p>
               </div>
               <div type="epigraph">
                  <pb facs="tcp:119587:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:119587:2"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>Jacob blessing his sons</figDesc>
                        <q>
                           <p>
                              <hi>And Iſrael ſtretched out his right hand</hi> &amp; <hi>laid it vpon Emphraims head, who was y: younger, and his left hand vpon Manaſſehs head: guiding his hands wittingly: for Manaſſeh was the firſt born.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <bibl>
                                 <hi>Gen: 48. ver: 14.</hi>
                              </bibl>
                           </p>
                        </q>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:119587:3"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:119587:3"/>
                  <head>TO THE READER.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">K</seg>Ing <hi>Solomon</hi> coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelled to <hi>take the little Foxes</hi>
                     <note n="a" place="margin">Cant. 2.15.</note> that <hi>ſpoiled the Vines and tender grapes,</hi> but King <hi>David</hi> his father paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately complained<note n="b" place="margin">Pſalm 80.13.</note> against the <hi>Boar</hi> of <hi>the Wood,</hi> and <hi>the wild beaſts of the Field that did waſt and devour the Vine that was brought out of</hi> Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt <hi>and had filled the Land.</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:119587:4"/>The Royal Prophet gives the Reaſon of that Ruine and deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, why the Vine was cut down and burnt up with fire<note n="c" place="margin">Pſalm. 80.12.</note> becauſe <hi>all her hedges and fences were broken down.</hi> This latter Age hath produced many ſuch wild and ſavage bruits, who Infatua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with Avarice and Ambition, have neither feared <hi>God</hi> nor honoured their <hi>King;</hi> nor ſpared any thing that was <hi>ſacred</hi> or <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign.</hi> The Riſe of their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly Principles and proceedings was m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>unted (doubtleſſe) from Infid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lity or Impiety, pride and diſobedience which precipitate a carnal mind into all varieties of deſperate Attempts; And through a want of the fear of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>true humility,</hi> a man (though
<pb facs="tcp:119587:4"/>a Rational Creature) is little bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then an Incarnate <hi>Devil.</hi> It is highly neceſſary therefore to build our Houſe a good Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation; that when the winds and ſtormes and waves ariſe &amp; blow and beat Againſt it, the Fabrick may neither ſhake nor fall. This may be moſt ſecurely done by Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Humility the <hi>baſis</hi> of our ſtructure, &amp; <hi>obedience</hi> a Corner ſtone more ſecurely to incement and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nite us towards God and towards Man: And this moſt clearly will have ſucceſse when it ſpringeth genuinely from this Native Root. Thus the Juice and Sap in the Winter courteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly returns towards the Roots to comfort their Mother, which in the Spring dutifully aſcends
<pb facs="tcp:119587:5"/>beautifying each branch and bow with Bloſſomes Leaves or Fruit, and ſo to make a thankfull Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to the beames of the Sun their Father. This duty of honour and reſpect to Parents, man may learn from the very vegetatives which ſpread forth their bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches as their hands and fingers towards Heaven, and at <hi>Autumn</hi> return a thankful ſacrifice; the Fruit that falls from their loaded and yielding Armes on their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Earth. It were a great ſhame for man the nobleſt Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to be guilty of Ingratitude; and as it is a foul Errour to be Accounted a harſh Parent, ſo it is a heavy crime to be look't upon as a diſhonouring or diſobedient Child.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:119587:5"/>
                  <p>Now that the Duties of theſe Relations may reciprocate with greater Comfort and advantage to all Parties Concerned; this Diſcourſe adventures abroad firſt, that Parents inſtructing their Children to practiſe the Duty of asking Bleſſing may be the better ſatisfied in the Truth, fitneſs, Cuſtom, and Innocency of their juſt Commands. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, That Children thus honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Parents, and depend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on their favour, and ſo daily craving their Bleſſings: may the more chearfully con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue their Teſtimonies of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour in their humble and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionate Comportment towards them: And ſo by this meaues A mutuall Communication of
<pb facs="tcp:119587:6"/>of Love and Honour, and the duty of asking Bleſſing in a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Civil and ſober behaviour, may more happily be derived to Poſterity. Thirdly, This may be as a Cordial to ſtrengthen and ſettle ſome weaker ſtomachs: which have been poyſoned or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with the Phariſaical Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven or New Doctrine of this la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Vertiginous Age, which in an Athenian humour or faction, hath gaped after nothing but Newes and Noveltie. Fourthly, The Conſcientious and Innocent pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of this Duty rightly ſet and ſtated (it is hoped) may prove as a Pilot: after theſe Stormes and Tempests of Vaſt Confuſion; to guide all ſober minded Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers into the Haven of Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
<pb facs="tcp:119587:6"/>and Peace, and that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Parents nor Childrens ſouls may be longer toſſed with e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very puff of new wind and facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous doctrine of humane and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porizing faction. Laſtly, as the Occaſion of this ſubject was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for better ſatisfaction, and to Remove all ſcruple and ſcandal in ſome of more tender Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: ſo it carrieth with it a Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did deſign towards all who ſhall read it, with ſome hopes that the Parental and Filial Duty firſt obſerved; True honour may aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend more properly and with plentifull Obedience towards the Civil and Spiritual Fathers of the Kingdom and Countrey.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>Farewell.</salute>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:119587:7"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119587:7"/>
                  <head>ΕΥΛΟΓΙΑ.</head>
                  <head type="sub">The Parents bleſſing the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient Children, and the childrens asking a bleſſing from their Parents, are pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous exerciſes, warrantable by the Word of God the Holy Scriptures.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. I.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ature, though ſhe ſeem Rude, and to govern by none but confuſed Rules, guideth Children to a du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful reſpect of their Parents, as well
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:119587:8"/>as Parents in a tender care towards their children. This mutual bond is twiſted by the hand of Providence, that Generations and Succeſſions may be derived to Poſterity. And if Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents did not cheriſh and nouriſh their children, they were in a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree more irrational then Beaſts. And if children ſhould not reflect with duty and kindneſſe on their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, they were little better then unthankful Devils.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 2.</head>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Reaſon, and all civil Relations enforce and perſwade the Parents care, and the childrens duty and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, without which Humane So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety would be diſſolved. For the unity of Government is firſt founded in the Family, and if the Relations of honour and obedience fail there, <hi>Homo homini Lupus.</hi> Man growes as ſavage as a Wolf.</p>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> And it is a certain Truth, that <hi>He who is undutiful to his natural Father:
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:119587:8"/>can neither be faithful to his Master the Aeconomical Father, nor loyal or obedient to the Supream Magiſtrate the King, who is the civil Father of the Countrey.</hi> Therefore it was the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination of <hi>Seneca:</hi> (a rational Heathen) <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>de Benef. cap.</hi> 3. <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes non amare, Impietas eſt, non ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſcere, Inſania eſt:</hi> That not to love Parents, was Impiety, but not to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge them, was bruitiſh Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Thus far Nature and Reaſon (though dim Lights) are able to Guide us.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 3.</head>
                     <p>But the Holy Scriptures ſend forth more bright Beams of Truth, and teach us that theſe holy Exerciſes of the Parents bleſſing their children, and the childrens begging a Bleſſing from their Parents, are warrantable, and conſonant to the word of God; Evidencing plainly their <hi>care &amp; ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe who Bleſſe,</hi> and <hi>their Honour, Reverence; and obedience who ask the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119587:9"/>Bleſſing.</hi> But that this Truth may be more clearly diſcerned, it is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry pertinent that it be rightly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood what it is (firſt) <hi>Benedicere to bleſſe,</hi> and (ſecondly) what it is <hi>Benedictionem petere</hi> to beg a Bleſſing.</p>
                     <p>To bleſſe is both attributed to God, and to his creatures:</p>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, to God: <hi>God created man in his own Image, and bleſſed them,</hi> Gen. 1.28. Thus Chriſt our Saviour <hi>bleſsed his Apoſtles,</hi> Luke 24.50, 51. In which place, both the Manner, and the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the Benediction is moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable: For, <hi>he lifted up his hands &amp; bleſsed them.</hi> And again, <hi>as he bleſſed them he was parted from them.</hi> This Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of Chriſts was attended with the Diſciples Adoration, <hi>Luke</hi> 24.52. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> they <hi>fell down,</hi> they <hi>bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their heads</hi> or bended their <hi>Knees:</hi> ſaith the Text, They <hi>worſhiped.</hi> And as Baptiſm is commanded <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> in the Name; ſo the bleſſing is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>: In the grace, love &amp; communion of the Father, the Son &amp; the Holy Ghoſt, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.13. Thus God bleſſed the creatures.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:119587:9"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 4.</head>
                     <p>The Creatures they <hi>Bleſſe</hi> like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe: ſo did the <hi>Angels bleſſe Jacob.</hi> Gen. 32.26. And the <hi>Patriarch would not let him go, until he had bleſſed him.</hi> Man alſo bleſſeth man. Thus <hi>Solomon the King bleſſed his Subjects,</hi> 1 King. 8.55. <hi>Aaron</hi> the Prieſt <hi>lift up his hand and bleſſed the people,</hi> Levit<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 9.22. <hi>Melchiſedeck bleſſed Abraham; the King of peace bleſſed the Patriarch, that mighty Warriour,</hi> Gen. 15.19. And as to the Paternal Benediction, <hi>Iſaac bleſſeth Jacob,</hi> Gen. 27.4, 25. and <hi>Eſau,</hi> Gen. 27.39, 40. and <hi>Jacob bleſſeth Joſeph and his two ſonnes,</hi> Gen. 48.9, 15. and <hi>Laban</hi> (though an uncircumciſed <hi>Canaanite,</hi> yet) had this ſpark of Grace in his heart, <hi>Gen.</hi> 31.55. <hi>Early in the morning he roſe up, and kiſſed his Sonnes and his Daughters, and bleſſed them.</hi> Yet if it be objected this was a Legal rather
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119587:10"/>then Evangelical practice; It is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered that <hi>S. Luke</hi> preſents <hi>Elizabeth</hi> pronouncing the <hi>Bleſſing</hi> to the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin <hi>Mary,</hi> Luke 1.42. <hi>Bleſſed art thou amongst women.</hi> And <hi>Simeon,</hi> Luk. 2.3. <hi>Bleſsing both Joſeph, and the Virgin Mary;</hi> and <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſeems to make <hi>Melchiſedeck's bleſsing</hi> of <hi>Abraham,</hi> Gen. 14.19. not only to be Legal but Evangelical, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.1, 6. and at the 7th. <hi>ver.</hi> plainly tels all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, both the Father and the Son, their duty, where the Apoſtle puts it out of all doubt <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> without contradiction: The Fathers duty is to bleſſe, the Son's to beg the Bleſſing, <hi>for the leſs is bleſſed of the Greater.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 5.</head>
                     <p>Now as the Scripture warranteth the Father in bleſſing his children: ſo it directeth the child how to beg his Fathers bleſſing. And therefore as we have underſtood Who is to bleſs; ſo it is neceſſary to know what it is
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:119587:10"/>
                        <hi>Benedicere</hi> to bleſſe. Benediction or Bleſſing hath a great Variety of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions in the Holy Scripture. 1. To Bleſs ſignifies to <hi>Praiſe,</hi> Pſ. 103.21, 22. 2. To <hi>give thanks,</hi> Gen. 14.20, 24, 27. 3. <hi>To conſecrate or ſanctifie,</hi> 1 Cor. 10.16. 4. <hi>To wiſh well to another,</hi> Gon. 47.7.10. 5. <hi>To of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer a preſent or gift,</hi> Gen. 33.11. 1 Sam. 25.27. 6. <hi>To encreaſe or multiply,</hi> Gen. 1.28. 7. <hi>To ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie and multiply,</hi> Matth. 14.19. 8. <hi>To adopt, and Agnize,</hi> Mark 10.16. Chriſt's proceeding there is an Example for the Parents tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to, and bleſſing of their obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent children, for in that paſſage there are five remarkable Circumſtances: 1. Chriſt's command; <hi>Suffer little children to come unto me, and forbid them not.</hi> 2. Chriſt's Declaration; <hi>of ſuch is the Kingdom of God.</hi> 3. His embracing, or Acceptation; <hi>He took them into his Armes.</hi> 4. The impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of his hands: <hi>he laid his hands upon them:</hi> 5. His Adoption of them; for he <hi>Bleſsed</hi> them: ſaying, <hi>of ſuch
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:119587:11"/>is the Kingdom of God.</hi> Now the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents bleſſing hath an Influence, or an Effect on all, or moſt of theſe kinds:</p>
                     <p>Firſt, the Parents bleſſe the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren when they <hi>Nouriſh</hi> them. This was <hi>Jacob</hi>'s care, <hi>Gen.</hi> 32.22,23.</p>
                     <p>Secondly, <hi>Education</hi> is the Parents Bleſſing, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.19. <hi>Acts</hi> 7.21, 22. <hi>Moſes</hi> was made happy this way; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Adopted Son of <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Daughter, and <hi>Learned in all the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the AEgyptians,</hi> and thereby made mighty in words and deeds. <hi>S. Paul</hi> hath made a Laſting Record of this kind of Bleſſing, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.5. <hi>of Lois and Eunice, who inſtructed Timothy in the Faith,</hi> though his father were a <hi>Greek,</hi> or <hi>Infidel,</hi> Acts 16.1. And it is from the Ground of his Education that <hi>S. Paul</hi> doth ſo ſtrictly charge his Diſciple <hi>Timothy,</hi>
                        <note n="*" place="margin">2 Tim. 3.14, 15.</note>
                        <hi>Continue thou in the things which thou hast learned, and haſt been aſſured of, knowing of whom thou haſt learned them, and that from a child thou haſt known the holy Scriptures.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Thirdly, Tender <hi>love</hi> and dear af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:119587:11"/>towards the children is a <hi>bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing</hi> of the Parents; which appeares eminently in thoſe holy Patriarchs, <hi>Jacob,</hi> and <hi>Joſeph</hi> towards their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, <hi>Gen.</hi> 42.36. <hi>Gen.</hi> 48.9.</p>
                     <p>Fourthly, <hi>Protection</hi>
                        <note n="a" place="margin">Gen. 33.13.</note>
                        <hi>Proviſion</hi>
                        <note n="b" place="margin">Gen. 25.5, 6.</note>
                        <hi>Counſel</hi>
                        <note n="c" place="margin">Gen. 27.43.</note>
                        <hi>Moderate Correction</hi>
                        <note n="d" place="margin">1 Sam. 2.23. Heb. 12.7.</note>
                        <hi>Care in their marriage</hi>
                        <note n="e" place="margin">Gen. 24.2. 4.</note>
                        <hi>Pardon for their faults</hi> [f] <hi>and prayer for their good</hi> [g] are all <hi>Bleſſings</hi> from the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to their children.<note n="h" place="margin">Job 1.5.</note>
                        <hi>Job</hi> is a rare Example in this kind; <hi>who ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified his Sons, Roſe up early in the Morning, and offered up burnt Offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, according to the Number of them all;</hi> For <hi>Job</hi> ſaid, <hi>It may be that my Sons have ſinned, and curſed God in their hearts. Thus did</hi> Job <hi>continually,</hi> his ſanctifying was doubtleſſe his Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of his Sons, wiſhing them well, and praying for them. By this it may more eaſily be concluded: firſt, who is, and ſecondly, what it is to Bleſſe. The Parents Relation thus explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, the Childrens will more orderly follow: whoſe duty it is to Beg, or ask their Parents Bleſsing.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:119587:12"/>
                     <head>Chap. 6.</head>
                     <p>God having given Lawes for his own Worſhip in the four firſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements: In the next words or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daineth Honour and Reverence to be exhibited to Parents, <hi>Exod,</hi> 20.12. <hi>Honour thy Father and thy Mother.</hi> From which words and Law (when we underſtand what is meant by <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi>) the Childrens duty will more clearly appear: Who, in order to the payment of that debt of <hi>Honour,</hi> they owe to their Parents: will be the better encouraged to practice that Humble and Religious duty, and not to think themſelves diſhonoured, or diſobliged if they beg, or daily ask their Parents bleſſing on their <hi>Knees,</hi> when they firſt ſee, or ſalute them in the Morning, or take leave of them at Night.</p>
                     <p>Moſt Writers and Expoſitors on the Fifth Commandement rather tell men what <hi>Honour</hi> imports, then what <hi>it is:</hi> and deſcribe the Concomitants
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:119587:12"/>or Conſequences, and Effects of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, but more ſparingly, or leſſe plainly ſet forth the Nature and Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of it. Therefore in this nice Point, it is highly Neceſſary to know what <hi>Honour</hi> (due from the children to the Parents) is.</p>
                     <p>Some conclude that <hi>Honour</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports three things in this Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement.</p>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, <hi>Obedience</hi> to their lawfull Commands:<note n="a" place="margin">Col. 3.20. Epheſ. 6.1.2.</note> And to confirm this, they inſtance in the Example of the <hi>Recabites,</hi> obeying the command of their father <hi>Jonadab,</hi> Jer. 35.8. Of <hi>Iſaac,</hi> ſubmitting to his fathers <hi>Knife</hi> to cut his innocent throat, <hi>Gen.</hi> 22.10. <hi>Of Chriſt,</hi> who went down with his <hi>Parents</hi> to <hi>Nazareth,</hi> and was <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, ſubject and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to them, <hi>Luke</hi> 2.51.</p>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, <hi>Honour</hi> imports <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence;</hi> which is diſcerned either by Words or Deeds, Thus King <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> ſeems to comment on the fifth Commandement, <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.22. <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour thy Father that begat thee, and thy
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:119587:13"/>Mother that bare thee, and deſpiſe her not.</hi> And as he was a Teacher, ſo he was a Practiſer and Example of this Duty, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 2.19. For, when his <hi>Mother</hi> approached near to ſpeak unto him, the <hi>King</hi> humbly ſaluted ſo dear a <hi>Subject; he roſe from his Throne to meet his Mother; he bowed himſelf unto her:</hi> Firſt begging her Bleſſing, not adventuring to return to his Throne untill he had Reveren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced her; and then as a dutiful <hi>Son, he cauſed a Seat to be ſet for the Kings Mother, and ſhe ſat at his right hand. Joſeph</hi> is ſuch another pattern of Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and Reverence towards his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Jacob.</hi> He was next to <hi>Pharaoh</hi> in <hi>AEgypt,</hi> and the King command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that the <hi>AEgyptians</hi> ſhould call him <hi>Abrech,</hi> Gen. 41.43. Which word hath a double ſignification in the Original: either tender Father, or Bow the head, and kneel down. The Militia of the Land was intirely in his Power, <hi>Gen.</hi> 41.40. <hi>At thy word ſhall all the people be Armed:</hi> and at the 44. <hi>ver. No man was to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:119587:13"/>dare to lift up his hand or foot without his Order.</hi> Yet this mighty Prince in his power and plenty, thinks him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf moſt happy when he hath but an Opportunity to <hi>Honour</hi> and Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence his aged <hi>Father,</hi> though but a meer <hi>Sphepheard,</hi> Gen. 47.4. and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy like a poor begger to ſtarve for bread. It is moſt eminently and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionately recorded, <hi>Gen.</hi> 46.29. how <hi>Joſeph</hi> made ready his <hi>Charret</hi> and went to <hi>Goſben</hi> to meet <hi>Iſrael</hi> his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and preſented himſelf unto him, (moſt probably firſt on his Knees) and fell on his Neck, and wept on his Neck a good while: and <hi>Joſeph</hi> who was ſtiled and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed <hi>Abrech,</hi> and had ſo many Knees bended to him: certainly he bended to his aged Father to gain a Bleſſing from him.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="chapter">
                     <head>Chap. 7.</head>
                     <p>A third importance of <hi>Honour,</hi> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> is Judged Maintenance; implying, that if the Parent be blind, the Son (as
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:119587:14"/>
                        <hi>Job, cap.</hi> 25.15.) is to be the Fathers <hi>Eye;</hi> if lame, the child is to be his Fathers <hi>foot</hi> or <hi>ſtaffe:</hi> Chriſt himſelf is an Example of this Duty, who (at his death) took care for his Mother the bleſſed Virgin, <hi>John</hi> 19.27. The Philoſopher thinks it reaſonable (<hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>t. Ethic. lib.</hi> 9. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. that chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren who have received life from their Parents, ſhould (to their utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt) endeavour to preſerve their Parents life. And ſome pious Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens are very famous even to theſe dayes, for their tender thankfulneſſe to their decrepid and aged Parents. By the help of theſe three Lights; Obedience, Reverence and Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, we perceive ſomewhat more, but not all that this Command, <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour thy Father and thy Mother,</hi> doth preſent.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 8.</head>
                     <p>The children are yet obliged to many other obſervant and dutiful Reſpects: For, as a Father hath
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:119587:14"/>the truſt and charge of many excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Relations and Priviledges, to be ſometimes Actively, ſometimes Paſſively manifeſted towards his children: ſo are children recipro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally charged with many ſingular Duties, which by the Lawes of God they are bound to repay, and Retri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute (on all Occaſions) to their ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-hearted Parents: as,</p>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, to <hi>Love</hi> them with cordial affection; Thus <hi>Eliſha</hi> beggeth of <hi>Elijah,</hi> 1 King. 19.20. when he had caſt his Mantle upon him, Let me I pray thee go and <hi>kiſſe my Father and Mother;</hi> (what may that otherwiſe ſignifie then to beg their bleſſing?) and <hi>take my leave of them:</hi> and then (ſaid <hi>Eliſha</hi>) I will follow thee; and <hi>Elijah</hi> thought it fit and neceſſary: <hi>Go; Return.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, It is a Teſtimony of the childrens honouring the Parents, when they not only bear with, but <hi>cover their Infirmities.</hi> Thus did <hi>Sem</hi> and <hi>Japhet,</hi> Gen. 9.23. when their Father was overcome with wine, <hi>they
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:119587:15"/>took a Mantle and put it on their ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and went backward, and covered the Nakedneſse of their Father with their faces backward, ſo that they ſaw not their Fathers Nakedneſſe.</hi> This bearing with, or rather hiding of their fathers Infirmity, procured a bleſſing on <hi>Sem</hi> and <hi>Japhet,</hi> Gen. 9.26, 27. But as a Father and a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, he denounceth a curſe on <hi>Cham</hi> and his poſterity, who had ſo undu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully derided, and diſhonoured his aged Father.</p>
                     <p>Thirdly, Honour ſignifies an <hi>hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſubmiſſion</hi> to the fathers Will; and <hi>Jeptha's</hi> daughter is ſuch an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of Obedience in this kind, that ſhe rather chooſeth to yield up her life at her fathers direction, then that he ſhould violate or once break his Vow, <hi>Judges</hi> 11.36, 37. Thus <hi>Samuel,</hi> though but an Infant, no ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er was weaned and parted from his Mothers breaſt; but was inſtantly removed from her company, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.24. <hi>And when his Mother had wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him, ſhe brought him to the Houſe of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:119587:15"/>the Lord in</hi> Shiloh, <hi>the child was young,</hi> as the original ſignifies, a very child when he <hi>miniſtred before the Lord, girded in a linnen Ephod,</hi> 1 Sam. 2.18. And no reaſon can be given of the Mothers parting with <hi>Samuel,</hi> or of the tender Infant's parting from his dear Mother, but that the child had as well an humble ſubmiſſion, as the Mother a Reſolution to make good her Vow, when ſhe begged her Son from God, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.11.</p>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, the honouring of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents ſtayed not here. S. <hi>Paul</hi> char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth children to <hi>Recompence</hi> their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents; Impoſeth this as a duty, as a Debt, not as an Act of Charity to ſupply their Neceſſity, but as ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to this kind of Gratitude. <hi>If any Widow hath children, let them first learn piety at home,</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.4. that is, to requite their Parents: Now that which is requited hath been former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly merited; And Recompence is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the conſcientious diſcharge of a ſpiritual or civil Debt, though
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:119587:16"/>it have no formal or legal Obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>in foro judicii;</hi> or in the Courts of earthly Judges: And it is Mr. <hi>Beza's</hi> Note on this place:<note place="margin">1 Tim. 5.4.</note>
                        <hi>Natura ipſa docet Majoribus vicem rependere, &amp; Deo gratum eſt hoc officium.</hi> The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiting of Parents is a Leſſon taught by Nature; A rational ſervice, and as a ſweet ſmelling ſacrifice, is gratefull and acceptable to God.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 9.</head>
                     <p>Theſe Beams will yet ſhine more brightly, and ſhew the Nature of Honour to Parents more perſpicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly if they be diſtinguiſhed from all other Qualities, which ſeem to be of like Relation or ſimilitude. For the word [<gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>] whether derived of the word <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, or <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, admits of great variety of ſignifications.</p>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> As firſt, <hi>Acceptation</hi> or <hi>Entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> John 4.44. A Prophet <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> is not without honour: that is, as S. <hi>Luke</hi> explains it, <hi>Luke</hi> 4.24. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>: a Prophet
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:119587:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>is not accepted in his own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey.</p>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, Civil Subordination, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.7. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. <hi>Render to all their dues, Honour; to whom Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour:</hi> So <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.1. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13. In both places is preſſed the duty of obeying Magiſtrates, and honouring the <hi>King.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, Honour ſignfies the <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue, rate</hi> or <hi>price</hi> of a thing. Thus the High Prieſt did uſe it, <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.6. crying out in their Hypocriſie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Judas,</hi> and the Traytors mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney; It is not lawful to put it into the Treaſury, becauſe it is <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>the price of blood.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, Dignity is comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded under the word <hi>Honour,</hi> Heb. 13.4. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>: Marriage is Honourable, or a Worthy Noble Relation.</p>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Fifthly, It ſignifies what is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly dear and precious, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.12. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, a precious Stone, <hi>Revel.</hi> 21.11. That Honour which children owe their Parents compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hendeth
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:119587:17"/>hendeth all theſe Parents may require and expect, and the children are obliged <hi>(ſine murmure)</hi> to pay all or any of their duties, when Occaſionally they ſhall require them from them.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 10.</head>
                     <p>The Schooles endeavour yet more Exactly to inſtruct children in the Leſſon of their duty towards their Parents: Acquainting us that Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour is <hi>Teſtimonium Excellentiae quae eſt in homine:</hi> A Teſtimony of that ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular Excellency that is in a Man. <hi>Tho. Aqu. 1<hi rend="sup">•</hi>. 2<hi rend="sup">d•ae</hi>. Qu.</hi> 2. <hi>Art.</hi> 1. And where can a child (though never ſo great, rich or wiſe) reflect with more admiration, then on the Excellency of his own Parents, from whom he hath received Life and Being?</p>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, They tell us that there is much difference between <hi>Laus, Gloria, Reverentia, &amp; Honor.</hi> That <hi>Laus tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eſt in Verbis, &amp; eſt reſpectu eorum quae ſunt ad finem.</hi> That praiſe chiefly
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:119587:17"/>conſiſts in verbal commendations, and is but converſant about thoſe things, that are only conducing to a further end: <hi>Tho. Aqu.</hi> 2<hi>
                           <hi rend="sup">a</hi>
                        </hi> 2<hi>
                           <hi rend="sup">d</hi>
                        </hi>
                        <hi>
                           <hi rend="sup">ae</hi> Qu.</hi> 103. <hi>Art.</hi> 1.</p>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, That <hi>Glory</hi> is not ſo much <hi>Honour,</hi> as an Effect of it; So the Philoſopher 1 <hi>Ethic. cap.</hi> 12. By this the goodneſs, worth and dignity of another is more clearly manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>Clareſcit Bonitas in notitia pluri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morum.</hi> And thence ſome will have <hi>Gloria,</hi> quaſi <hi>Claria,</hi> or <hi>Clara cum Laude Notitia;</hi> A more bright and ſplendent Knowledge. ſo <hi>S. Ambr.</hi> and <hi>S. Auguſt.</hi> gloſs on the Word.</p>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, That <hi>Reverence</hi> is ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a part of <hi>Honour,</hi> then Honour it ſelf. For whether it be perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in word or deed, by a venerable Eſtimation ariſing from the mind, or an humble comportment from the Body: yet it is but as the branch to the Root, as a way leading to ſome further End; <hi>Principium motivum,</hi> a principle Motive, or preparation of him who Reverenceth, and not the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:119587:18"/>compleat Honour that is due to him who is Reverenced, <hi>Tho. Aqu.</hi> 2<hi>
                           <hi rend="sup">a</hi>
                        </hi> 2<hi>
                           <hi rend="sup">dae</hi> Qu.</hi> 103. <hi>ad Arg.</hi> 1.</p>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, The Schooles affirm that <hi>Honor</hi> amongſt all External good things is the chiefeſt: becauſe it is <hi>Praemium virtutis &amp; Testimonium Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellentiae. Tho. Aq.</hi> 1<hi>
                           <hi rend="sup">a</hi>
                        </hi> 2<hi>
                           <hi rend="sup">d</hi>
                        </hi>
                        <hi>
                           <hi rend="sup">ae</hi> queſt.</hi> 2<hi>
                           <hi rend="sup">d</hi>
                        </hi>
                        <hi>
                           <hi rend="sup">o</hi> Art.</hi> 2<hi>
                           <hi rend="sup">d</hi>
                        </hi>
                        <hi>
                           <hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</hi> the reward of Vertue, and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Teſtimony of Worth and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency. Now as the Objects do di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſificate, and vary in their worth &amp; praeeminency; ſo do the Agents in their. Influences and diſpoſitions. And therefore becauſe none do come in the Scales of compariſon with Parents in their relation to their children; therefore the <hi>Honour</hi> due unto them ought to be the ſincereſt, the exacteſt, the Higheſt, and next to that which is due to God, the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty Father of all. And hence it is that there followeth another Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luation, which the Learned put upon honour, before Love. For the child who truly honours his Father, aymeth particularly at his Fathers good; but
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:119587:18"/>Love and Charity hath a more Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Object, ſpreading its Grace U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſally on all: <hi>Honor reſpicit pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prium Bonum honorati; ſed Amor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicit Bonum in Communi. Tho. Aqu.</hi> 2<hi>a</hi> 2<hi>
                           <hi rend="sup">d</hi>
                        </hi>
                        <hi>
                           <hi rend="sup">ae</hi>. qu.</hi> 25. <hi>Art.</hi> 1. <hi>Arg.</hi> 3. Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans love their Brethren as Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans; but children honour their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents not only as Chriſtians, but as Chriſtian children; obliged to that ſingular Duty by God himſelf, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.12. Now a the beams of the Sun when they concenter in one point are more Energetical and operative, then when the Rayes of that glorious Body are in their diffuſion: ſo is it with children, who truly honour their Parents: Their dutifull affections being terminated and fixed in a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Object of honouring their Parents, the Effect is of greater force; the duty better performed; the parents more highly honoured: and God who commands the duty, better ſerved and obeyed.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="11" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:119587:19"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 11.</head>
                     <p>Neither is it ſufficient that chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren hounour their Parents in their <hi>heart</hi> only, but likewiſe they are to perform it by their outward <hi>Signes, teſtimonies and Geſtures:</hi> The reaſon is, <hi>Quia honor, quoad Deum, potest eſſe in ſolo Corde; ſed quoad hominem, est in ſignis exterioribus. Tho. Aq. Quaeſt.</hi> 103. <hi>Art.</hi> 1. God who is a Spirit, is the Searcher of the heart, and can faſhion, and find out all the thoughts and ſecret motions of the mind and ſoul; but Man is a limited creature, and can only Judge by the viſible or external Actions. So then it is not enough for children only cordially, but corporally, and with Reverential exteriour Geſtures to honour and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect their <hi>Parents.</hi> The Propoſitions made ſo evident and plain, the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion may the better follow; That it is Warrantable by Gods Word, Expedient and Lawfull, that chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren crave &amp; ask their Parents bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:119587:19"/>In which Religious Exerciſes theſe three Advantages muſt needs follow: Firſt, that God hereby is <hi>obeyed,</hi> and better ſerved. Secondly, the Parents more highly <hi>honoured</hi> and Eſteemed. Thirdly, the children are more certainly <hi>Bleſſed</hi> and comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="12" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 12.</head>
                     <p>Firſt, The child asking his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Bleſſing; by this pious duty God is <hi>Glorified.</hi> In the primitive age of the World the holy Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archs and fathers of Families, were conſtituted <hi>Kings, Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets</hi> in their patenal Juriſdiction: <hi>Kings,</hi> to rule and Govern; <hi>Prieſts,</hi> to pray and ſanctifie; <hi>Prophets,</hi> to teach and Inſtruct their Families. Theſe Offices were very eminently performed by <hi>Abraham,</hi> who was King and Soveraign Commander, when his kinſman <hi>Lot</hi> was taken pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner and made a captive? <hi>armed his trained ſervants born in his own houſe?
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:119587:20"/>three hundred and eighteen, and purſued them to</hi> Dan, <hi>and he divided himſelf againſt them, he and his ſervants, by might, and ſmote them, and purſued them to</hi> Hoba, <hi>which is on the left hand of</hi> Damaſcus, <hi>and he brought back all the goods, and his Brother</hi> Lot <hi>and his goods, and all the Women alſo, and all the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> Gen. 14.14, 15, 16. As a Prieſt, he refuſed not to ſacrifice his only Son; <hi>Senile pignus, &amp; ſemen promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum;</hi> but (commanded by God) laid his child on the Altar and <hi>ſtretched out his hand to have ſlain him, had not the Angel of God restrained him,</hi> Gen. 22.9, 10, 11. verſes. God is pleaſed to acknowledge him a <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet</hi> alſo, and to bleſſe him; and tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth man why he bleſſeth him: <hi>For I know that</hi> Abraham <hi>will command his children and his houſhold after him, and they ſhall keep the Way of the Lord to do juſtice and Judgement,</hi> Gen. 18.18, 19. Now we are the children of the prophets, <hi>Acts</hi> 3.25. the ſons of <hi>Abraham,</hi> if we do the works of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,</hi> John 8.39. Gal. 3.8. And in
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:119587:20"/>this reſpect, when the child asketh his Fathers bleſſing, and thereby ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth a Royal, parental, and Soveraign power in the Father, who by Gods Law is to rule and govern his children: he honoureth God, whoſe Image and Authority (as a Vicegerent on Earth) the Father re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenteth, by regulating his children and ſervants. But the Father is not only to be honoured, as having a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Soveraign Truſt from God, but as a <hi>Prieſt,</hi> who (after <hi>Jobs</hi> example) Job 1.5. <hi>riſeth up early every morning and offereth burnt offerings, and every night burneth Incenſe;</hi> that is, <hi>prayeth with, or for his Family both Morning and Evening.</hi> And therefore the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren daily craving a Bleſſing from their Parents, who pray for them, God is hereby glorified, and (this Law being more exactly obſerved every morning and evening) He is better ſerved. Again, Parents are not only as our oeconomical <hi>Kings</hi> to govern us, &amp; our Prieſts to pray with and for us; but they are as our <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets</hi>
                        <pb n="28" facs="tcp:119587:21"/>to inſtruct us. In this Relation we owe them continual <hi>honour,</hi> and conſtant <hi>Reverence.</hi> The Argument is a <hi>minore ad majus,</hi> from <hi>S. Pauls</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the <hi>Heir,</hi> who, <hi>as long as he is a child, differeth nothing from a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, though he be lord of all jure haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditario:</hi> but is <hi>under Tutors and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours, untill the time appointed by the Father,</hi> Gal. 4.1, 2. Now if a fatherleſſe heir owe ſuch Exact duty to Tutors and Governours; and a living child to the Commands, or Teſtament of a dead Father, what Honour and Obedience doth a child owe to a living Father or Mother, who as Prophets teach and inſtruct them daily? So then to ask their Bleſſing, who have ſuch care of their ſouls &amp; bodies, is a teſtimony of their care to keep Gods Law; and hereby alſo God is more glorified. For if Heires owe ſo much Reverence and reſpect to civil Tutors and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, how humble and obedient ought children to be to their Natural and tender Parents?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="13" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:119587:21"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 13.</head>
                     <p>There is yet another Argument which ſeemeth very ſtoutly to preſs children to the the Religious practice of asking bleſſing, becauſe the holy Commandements of God were pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marily and chiefly recommended to the Fathers and the heads or Maſters of Families. This is evident in the Scripture; for <hi>Moſes</hi> deſcending from the Mount, he called for the <hi>Elders</hi> of the people, that is, the <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> or <hi>chiefest</hi> of the Tribes and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, <hi>Exod.</hi> 19.7. and laid before their faces all the Words which the Lord commanded him: and at the 14, 15. <hi>verſes Moſes</hi> prepared the people to receive the Law with a Bleſſing of Sanctification. See and obſerve Gods own Order and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod. <hi>God</hi> bleſſeth <hi>Moſes,</hi> and <hi>Moſes</hi> bleſſeth the <hi>Elders</hi> of the people, the <hi>Fathers;</hi> and the <hi>Fathers</hi> they are to bleſs their <hi>children.</hi> This Argument is yet corroborated, and ſtrengthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:119587:22"/>from the Moral Law it ſelf; where for Method, God having command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed our duties to him in the firſt Table, immediately requireth chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in the firſt Commandement of the ſecond Table to <hi>honour</hi> their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents: as next to God, or in Gods place on earth, or becauſe the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of this one Commandement might cauſe (infallibly) Diſorder, and Violation of all the reſt. And as the fifth Commandement is pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary in the ſecond Table for Order; ſo for matter. In all the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements their obſervation ſeems chiefly recommended to the Exact care of the Fathers or Maſters of the Families, who are obliged to teach their children, and their Childrens children from generation to genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And the fourth Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to this purpoſe is not only <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perative,</hi> but <hi>Authoritative</hi> in Parents and Maſters; where it is evident and plain, though the duties of the ten Commandements are of Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal concernment to all Ages and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple;
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:119587:22"/>Yet <hi>Parents</hi> and <hi>Maſters</hi> have a more particular charge flowing from the Words of that Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement. Remember that <hi>thou</hi> keep holy the Sabbath day. <hi>Thou</hi> ſhalt do no manner of work, <hi>Thou nor thy Son, nor thy Daughter, nor thy man-ſervant, nor thy maid-ſervant, nor thy Cattel, nor the ſtranger that is within thy Gates.</hi> So that, in ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of Gods Truſt: the <hi>Fathers</hi> and <hi>Masters</hi> of Families are <hi>Cuſtodes utriuſ<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> Tabulae,</hi> Deut. 6. v. 7, 8. the Conſervators of Gods Lawes; which though commanding all, yet particularly are recommended to their charge, as to thoſe who are not only bound to give an account for themſelves, but for their <hi>children,</hi> their <hi>ſervants,</hi> their <hi>cattel,</hi> and the <hi>ſtranger that is within their Gates.</hi> The Caſe thus ſtated, the Parents being in ſo high and Immediate Truſt from God; what duty can be too humble, or too often from the children to their Parents? Who cannot but put a high Reputation in
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:119587:23"/>the preſence of God, Angels and men, on their Humility, when they <hi>Bow their bodies, and Bend their Knees, and crave, as their daily bread from God, ſo a daily Bleſſing from their Parents.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="14" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 14.</head>
                     <p>The Truth thus opened, it may without ſcruple or danger be apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the moſt tender conſcience; and without any ſnares to ſin, or jug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſubtile ſophiſtry, that the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> where the Parents uſe to bleſſe their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, humbly, daily begging their Bleſſing; is a moſt Religious practice, conſonant, and not repugnant, expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient, &amp; not forbidden by the Word of God.</p>
                     <p>Yet two ſorts of Objections may ſeem to ariſe, and ſo firſt ſtartle, and amaze, then deter and diſwade from this pious Exerciſe. To ſome this may appear ſomewhat ſuperſtitious, or to lean and encline too much to
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:119587:23"/>Popery and Idolatry: But to free all from ſuch erroneous deluding opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, doubts, fear or danger; there is no ſpice of Idolatry, nor any ſuch unclean drug, or ill ingredient in this innocent compoſition of begging the Parents bleſſing. As to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſt: Firſt, It is a practiſe rarely uſed or known in ſome Roman-Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Countreys; Or rather cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly not taught in the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> ſo that the <hi>Italians, Spaniſh, Germanes</hi> and <hi>French</hi> (for the moſt part) uſe it not: And it may be very probable for this Reaſon, that the Parents having leſs Reverence from their children, and the Children leſs honour for their Parents; the Popiſh Prieſts might more ſecurely and craftily enſnare, and ſubjugate the mutual Relations of both parents and children entirely to themſelves: e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially then, when they are chain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to them on their bended knees in their Auricular duties; and anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſuch Queſtions, as are propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to them, when they are opening
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:119587:24"/>their hearts in an humble and peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Confeſſion. The Doctrine of which Confeſſion (if rightly uſed, and as Chriſt hath recommended to his Church) is of as much comfort, as truth; founded on Chriſt's own Command, <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.28. which words <hi>Venite ad Me</hi> are explained, <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.40, to Me: that is, in my Abſence to my Apoſtles, and their lawful and right Succeſſors, the vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant Biſhops, and faithful Paſtors of Gods Church: whoſe Commiſſion is large, and will continue in force to the end of the World <hi>in haec verba; Verily I ſay unto you, whatſoever ye bind on earth, ſhall be bound in heaven, and what ſoever ye looſe on earth, ſhall be looſed in heaven,</hi> Matth. 18.18. And it is an Infallible truth, that the lawfull Paſtors only are Miniſterial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and moſt properly truſted with hearing penitent Confeſſions, and then giving and pronouncing Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution in the Name of the Father, the Son, and the Holy Ghoſt, to the quieting of the troubled ſpirit and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:119587:24"/>wounded Conſcience of the humble &amp; repenting Sinner. Yet there are E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelical Steps which lead children to a dutifull confeſſion of their faults and offences to their compaſſionate Parents. This is moſt eminent in the poor broken hearted relenting Prodigal, who firſt Reſolveth on his Confeſſion: ſaying, <hi>I will go to my Father, and</hi> then perfecteth his Reſolution, by acknowledging his er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, firſt accuſing, then proclaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt himſelf, <hi>Father, I have ſinned against heaven and before thee, I am no more worthy to be called thy Son.</hi> Luke 15.18, 19, 20, 21. On which words Mr. <hi>Beza</hi> (though no Patron of the Doctrine or practiſe of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion in the people, or abſolution from the Venerable Paſtor of Gods Church) hath this Note (of which ſome preſent advantage may be made) <hi>In vera Reſipiſcentia ineſt ſenſus peccati cum triſtitia &amp; pudore conjunctus, unde naſcitur Confeſsio, quam ſequitur Abſolutio:</hi> that is, There is a ſenſe of ſin in Repentance con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:119587:25"/>and mixed with ſhame and ſorrow for it; hence ſprings an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious and free Confeſſion, which is recompenced with the Act of gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Remiſſion, or Abſolution by compaſsionate parents. And as Confeſſion of ſinnes to the Parents, craving their pardon, or begging their Bleſſing is not ſinfull, whether the P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>piſts uſe it or uſe it not: So <hi>Quoad Rem,</hi> it is not ſuperſtitious, and ſo <hi>praeter,</hi> or <hi>contra verbum Dei,</hi> that is, without Warrant from, or againſt the Word of God. To make this more clear, it is neceſſary that it be rightly underſtood, that Superſtition is <hi>vitium Religioni oppoſitum ſecundum exceſſum, quo quis divinum exhibet Cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum vel cui non debet, vel non eo modo quo debet,</hi> Tho. Aq. 2<hi rend="sup">a</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">dae</hi>. qu. 92. Art. 1. that is, Superſtition is an er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour oppoſing true Religion in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, giving or Attributing divine Worſhip where it is not due or law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, or a worſhipping the true God after a ſuperſtitious and falſe man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manner. But the honour that Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:119587:25"/>may juſtly expect, and children are obliged dutifully to pay, is ſo far from being an Errour, that it is a Truth, ſo far from being ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, that it is neceſſary; and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren ſeldom or never are found guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of an exceſs of their obedience to their Parents; and therefore the duty being commanded and requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by God, the children are obliged to honour their Parents; in which holy Exerciſe there cannot be the leaſt fear, or danger, or tincture of ſuperfluity or Superſtition.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="15" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 15.</head>
                     <p>And whereas ſome may object, that the begging of the Parents bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing on their Knees may Rob God of his Worſhip, or reliſh of Idolatry: (which is a moſt heinous ſin, as di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly thwarting and oppoſing the very Letter of the firſt and ſecond Commandements of the Moral law:) Let ſuch Inventors of dangerous O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions know, that he who comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:119587:26"/>the keeping of One, expecteth the keeping and obſervation of all the Law; and he that is guilty of the breach of one, is guilty of all. This is the Method of S. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf; arguing with the Rabbies and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors of his Age: <hi>Thou therefore that teacheſt another, teacheſt thou not thy ſelf? Thou that teacheſt a man ſhould not ſteal, doeſt thou ſteal? Thou that ſayeſt a man ſhould not commit Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, doſt thou commit Adultery? thou that abhorreſt Idols, doſt thou commit ſacriledge?</hi> Rom. 2.21, 22. From all theſe concluding Queſtions it may be Logically, and rationally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, that he that leſſeneth or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibiteth the childrens duty in the moſt Reverend and humble manner towards the Parents: doth either weakly erre in Judgement, or cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly dawb with untempered mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar; hypocritically pretending zeal to God, but not ſincerely intending his Divine Worſhip; when, for Gods Commandements, men dare to ſhuffle in their own Doctrines and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:119587:26"/>Traditions, and (on pretence of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry) exempt, or diſcourage the children from their duties towards their Parents. This was the <hi>Phariſees</hi> own Way long ſince, condemned by Chriſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 15.56. who taught the World a better Leſſon, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded himſelf, that honouring of parents is not Idolatry: which ſin (if rightly underſtood) is an exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biting or devoting and giving that worſhip to the creature, which is only and divinely due to God. So <hi>Tho. Aq.</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">a</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">dx</hi>. <hi>qu.</hi> 94. <hi>art.</hi> 1. <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latria eſt exhibere Latriam (id eſt) cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum Dei Creaturae.</hi> This is certainly an high and moſt horrid ſinne: But children are not to honour their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents as God, but as Men, and not only as Men, but as Parents; and not ſo much becauſe their Parents ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, or require their Duty, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God directs, and commands the performance of it. God is to be loved and ſerved with all our hearts, with all our minds, with all our ſoules, and our Neighbours are
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:119587:27"/>to be loved as our ſelves. And as to our Parents they are to be honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as God hath commanded; which duty cannot be performed without the treble Obſervation of Natural, Civil and Moral reſpects. Nature teacheth to be affectionate, becauſe the are our <hi>Generators:</hi> Civility ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligeth us to them, becauſe they are or have been <hi>Conſervators:</hi> And there is a Moral reſpect due to them, which ſtrictly binds the conſcience becauſe of Gods Commandements; All theſe ought and may be done, without ſuſpition of the groſs and horrid ſin of Idolatry.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="16" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 16.</head>
                     <p>To others the practiſe of asking the Parents Bleſſing ſeems of Novel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or Work derogatory from the Worſhip and honour of God: And thus are ſome ſeperated, and have ſtarted aſide from this holy pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe, fearing or at leaſt reſuſing to give their Parents that honour,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:119587:27"/>which God commands, out of a ſingular, or ſelf-opinion, that giving ſo much as is due to their Parents, they may not Reſerve, or ſo ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently Worſhip God as he requires. Our Saviour Chriſt ſeems to take notice of ſuch humorous and Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſaical and phanatick conceipts, ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing from the heads of ſome ſchiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical Innovators, when he lived on earth. The place is very worthy of ſingular obſervation, recorded by Saint <hi>Matthew,</hi> from the firſt to the tenth <hi>verſe</hi>
                        <note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 15.1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> of the fifteenth <hi>Chapter,</hi> where the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees</hi> bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly make the aſſault, or on-ſet on Chriſt, demanding a reaſon, <hi>ver.</hi> 2. <hi>why do thy Diſciples tranſgreſs the Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of the Elders? for they waſh not their hands, when they eat bread.</hi> Chriſt ſuddenly makes a Reply by another Queſtion, <hi>ver.</hi> 4. <hi>Why do ye alſo tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe the Commandements of God by your Traditions?</hi> implying, that as the God of <hi>Iſrael</hi> was above the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> ſo the Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God above the Lawes of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:119587:28"/>Men, and Traditions of the Elders. And then Chriſt tells them of their ſin, and Tranſgreſſion, <hi>ver.</hi> 4. God commanded, ſaying, <hi>Honour thy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Mother, Exod.</hi> 20.12. <hi>Deut.</hi> 5.16, <hi>and he that curſeth Father or Mother let him die the death,</hi> Levit. 20.9. Prov. 20.20. Having ſet down the Law, and detected their Hypocriſie and ſinne, he further ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gueth, <hi>ver.</hi> 5. But ye ſay, whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſhall ſay to his father or mother it is <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, or as it is Originally in St. <hi>Mark,</hi> chap. 7.11. <hi>Corban,</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>a Gift by whatſoever thou might<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt be profited by me,</hi> &amp;c. (as it followeth <hi>Matth.</hi> 15.16.) <hi>and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour not his father or his mother, ſhall be free.</hi> From theſe obſervations and Objections Chriſt inferreth and preſſeth this Concluſion; <hi>Thus, or therefore have ye made the Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God of none Effect by your Traditions:</hi> and then accuſeth them, as diſſembling Hypocrites, of whom <hi>Iſaiah</hi> propheſied, <hi>This people draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth nigh unto me with their mouth, but
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:119587:28"/>their heart is far from me,</hi> Eſay 29.18. <hi>But in vain do they worſhip me, teaching for doctrines the Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Men, or Directories of meer hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Invention.</hi> This Argument of Chriſts, which ſo plainly accuſeth the <hi>Jewes</hi> of their Impi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>y towards their Parents, may Invite Chriſtians to more exact performance of their Reverence and Duty towards their <hi>Parents;</hi> Inaſmuch as this Law is not only proclaimed by <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the Miniſtration of the Angels, nor only written by the finger of God; but alſo often preached and publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the World by <hi>Christ,</hi> the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Word of God; greater then <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> or <hi>Solomon,</hi> or all the ſonnes of Men.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="17" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 17.</head>
                     <p>It is remarkable in this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> that <hi>Chriſts</hi> method and <hi>Moſes</hi>'s differ in the diſtribution of this Law <hi>(viz.)</hi> Honour thy Father and Mother. For,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:119587:29"/>when <hi>Moſes</hi> delivered it to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: it was accompanied with a <hi>Promiſe,</hi> That thy dayes may be long in the Land, which the Lord thy God giveth thee: But the two Evangeliſts, both St. <hi>Matthew</hi> and St. <hi>Mark</hi> (in the places cited before) preſent our Saviour teaching the Commandement either ſtrictly in the Duty, (<hi>viz.</hi>) Honour thy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and thy Mother; or elſe (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out mentioning of the Bleſſing or Promiſe) threatning the diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence thereof, poſitively with a curſe, <hi>Dominus hic Praemium praetermittit, ponit, quod terribilius eſt, ſcilicet, Poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam; ut &amp; ipſos ſtupefaceret, &amp; alios attraheret. Chryſost, Hom,</hi> 12. Levit. 20.9. He that curſeth Father or Mother let him die the death: as if Chriſt had ſaid, He that neglecteth his duty, or deſpiſeth or diſhonour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his Parents, is ſo far from pity or pardon, that he deſerves to die the death. Thus Chriſt ſeems to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute with Indignation thoſe who ſhould prove Violaters of this Law.
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:119587:29"/>And if there be any Branches of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſobedience (as it is probable too many) in this Phariſaical hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Age; Chriſt hath diſcovered the bitter Root from whence they ſpring: that is, from the vain Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of ſome Schiſmatical and phariſaical Directors ſeditiouſly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected: or from Diſobedient children, who (as the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees</hi> of old) prefer the New and ſingular Opinions and Traditions of ſome Giddy-brain'd Teachers, before the Commandements of God. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ought any to fear that God is leſſened in his honour, if the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents are Revereneed by their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, but on the contrary God is more abundantly, and highly Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured in the performance of this Duty: becauſe, firſt, his Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement is obſerved: ſecondly, by this meanes children are (as on a lad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der or ſcale) to climb up the higher towards God, the Almighty Father of Heaven and Earth: thirdly, by this humble deportment, taught by
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:119587:30"/>Chriſt in his Goſpel, they more In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocently avoid the cenſure and ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pition of Hypocriſie: fourthly, they more ſecurely keep and preſerve themſelves from Gods curſe and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation: and laſtly, they more happily obtain the Bleſſing promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, both in this life, and that which is to come.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="18" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 18.</head>
                     <p>To all this it may be further ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and juſtly pleaded, that Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Reverence is to be given from children to their Parents, not only becauſe they are Generators, but <hi>Parents, Patres &amp; Matres:</hi> not only their begetters, but their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and Mothers, which are terms of kindneſſe, and rather proper then common Names in their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, ſounding out nothing but ſweetneſſe, tenderneſſe, care, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and compaſſion. Thus the Learned comment upon the words: <hi>Pater &amp; Mater Nomina Pietatis; of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiorum
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:119587:30"/>Vocabula, naturae Vincula.</hi> St. Hierom de vita Eremit. ad Helio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorum. They are pious Relations, and Bonds of Natural affection. <hi>A. mor &amp; honor,</hi> love and honour chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly differing <hi>modo operandi,</hi> in the manner of Operation; Love natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally deſcends from the Parents to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the children <hi>Deſcendit amor, aſcendat honor,</hi> Love runnes as the ſtream from the Fountain, Honor, as an high and fruitfull Tide, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns fully and freely towards the Fountain. And therefore Honour ſhould plentifully, and ſupernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally and ſpiritually commanded by God own Word and Lawes. If yet any enquire how, that is, in what manner, or how often, that is, at what times, the Parents ſhould bleſs their children, or the children beg their Parents bleſſing? it may be eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly anſwered, The Parents are firſt directed to have a Preparation, and Inclination to bleſſe their Obedient
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:119587:31"/>children at all times: but (if there be conveniency or occaſion) to bleſs them particularly every Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and Evening, that the Sun of the Firmament may not ſet, or riſe again on the wrath, neglect, or Diſcontent of ſuch near, and dear Relations. And this bleſſing is not to paſs ſlightly, or curſorily; but with great regard to what is done. For the Fathers bleſſing is not only a Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of Love to his child, but a prayer to God for him, a part of the Fathers daily Devotion for his child to God; and a kind of Recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation or Dedication of his child for Gods further bleſſing. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this picus Practice is to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed with greater care, that God may be more ſincerely glorified, the Parents bleſſing may be more truly honoured, and the children receiving this grace and favour, may be more certainly bleſſed. This Rule well obſerved, the Parents will not take the Name of God in vain. For the Bleſsing thus imparted with Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:119587:31"/>and godly fear; God is daily honoured hereby, and whether the Bleſsing from the Parents be a <hi>Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> to God, or a <hi>Testimony</hi> of paternal affection; or an <hi>earneſt</hi> and pledg of future Kindneſſe and Benevolence from the Indulgent Parents to the Obedient children; God cannot but be well pleaſed, where parents are ſo tender and carefull firſt of Gods Honour, and then of their own.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="19" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 19.</head>
                     <p>Another, or ſecond Queſtion is, How, that is, in what manner, or how often that is, at what times it may be expedient for children to make their Addreſſes to their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents. It may be anſwered to the firſt Quaere; (How?) that they are to addreſs to their Parents in the moſt Reverend geſture, and moſt humble poſture, and behaviour. No Law or Reaſon Will, or Can aſſert the contrary, and if uncovering of the Head, bowing of the Body, bend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:119587:32"/>of the Knee; all of theſe, or ſome of theſe be civilly allowed from Subjects to their Soveraigns, from the people to their Magiſtrates (ſo that they are commanded to kneel at their Barres) or from ſervants to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their Maſters; Parents may expect as much if not more, from their children addreſſing to them not only in a civil, but a Conſcientious and venerable Comportment, to beg their Bleſsing. And it is very ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable to this purpoſe, that as God reſtrained in the ſecond ommande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: ſaying, <hi>Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelf any graven Image, Thou ſhalt not Bow down and Worſhip:</hi> So affirmatively, or poſitively in the fifth Precept of the ſecond Table, he commandeth, Honour thy Father and Mother; and this Honour is not to be performed but <hi>verbis, &amp; Signis,</hi> in words, ſignes, or exterior deeds: and therefore uncovering of the Head, bowing of the Body or bend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Knee, are commendable and expedient geſtures in craving
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:119587:32"/>or begging the Parents Bleſſing? And <hi>St. Paul</hi> ſetting forth to the whole world his Eccleſiaſtical Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, by his Apoſtolical Juriſdiction, amongſt other things, charged this upon the Church of <hi>Corinth;</hi> that they ſhould be Reverend Hearers of Gods Word, and Reverend Recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of Gods holy Sacraments; plainly declaring that <hi>every man</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>) <hi>whether Father, or child pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or propheſying, his Head being co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, diſhonoureth his Head,</hi> 1 Cor. 11.4. On which Words Mr. <hi>Beza</hi> hath put forth this Note: <hi>Hinc Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligit viros, ſi operto Capite (quod tum habebatur ſubjectionis ſignum) publicis caetibus ad audiendum verbum, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipiendas preces coactis interſint, ſua veluti dignitate ſeipſos privare, contra Dei Ordinationem. That is,</hi> * If men being preſent in the publike Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation to hear the Word of God, or joyn in prayers, had their heads covered: they did deprive them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <hi>(ipſo facto)</hi> of that Dignity God had given them, againſt Gods
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:119587:33"/>Ordinance. As for the Parentheſis, though it be Tranſlated among the Authors Notes, yet it hath not a Warrantable Teſtimony of Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to defend that Aſſertion. And Mr-<hi>Beza</hi> is very bold with St. <hi>Paul,</hi> to conclude his Rule and Canon to be only Temporal and Politick, as it is his Note on the ſame Words: but it is probable, that which S. <hi>Paul</hi> preached at <hi>Corinth</hi> for Reverence, decency and Order in Gods Church, was not ſo well taught, or ſo well Learn't at <hi>Geneva.</hi> However, from this Doctrine and Order of St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Conſtitution, children may learn to be uncovered, to bend their Knees, and to be Reverent in their behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our; when they come to crave their Parents Bleſſing, as being the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Prieſts of the Families, who Inſtruct them, ond daily pray with and for them. And if the ſons of <hi>Noah</hi> were ſo exceedingly modeſt, that they durſt not ſo much as peep or look at their Fathers Infirmity, but went backward with their<note place="margin">* Quo ad unc habe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batur ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectionis Signum.</note>
                        <pb n="53" facs="tcp:119587:33"/>Mantles upon their ſhoulders, <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.23. to hide his Nakedneſſe, with what great Reverence and humility, bending, bowing, or kneeling, may it be concluded that <hi>Shem</hi> and <hi>Japhet</hi> came unto their Father, when they received his Bleſsing? <hi>Gen</hi> 9.26, 27. From all theſe Arguments, it cannot but be allowable, expedient and Warrantable, for children craving their Parents Bleſsing, to <hi>kneel</hi> and <hi>beg</hi> it in the moſt dutifull and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſt geſture; The Parents being as <hi>Joſephs</hi> Sheafe; their children round about their Table are to Bow and make obeyſance to them, <hi>Gen.</hi> 37.7. And though the children be as glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious as the Sun, the Moon, or the Starres for Honour, Riches, Power, or any other Excellency: yet ſtill they are obliged to honour their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, and to Bow down themſelves unto them even to the Earth, <hi>Gen.</hi> 37. <hi>ver.</hi> 10. A<note n="*" place="margin">Sir <hi>Tho. Moore,</hi> L. Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> in K. <hi>Henry</hi> the eighths time.</note> Countryman of our own (as the Hiſtory Relates) had this humility and honour for his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, as he approached near to
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:119587:34"/>them, when he was in a far higher Degree of civil Honour, then his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to fall down on his Knees and ask his Bleſsing: And it was a very high Example; pious and commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable in thoſe two Princes, the one a Son, the other a Mother; the Son a King, the Mother a Queen, yet a Subject: to ſee them ſtrive which ſhould be firſt on their Knees; the Son (a King) to ask his Mothers Bleſſing; or the Mother (a Subject) to kiſs her Sons, a Kings hands; And it was no leſſe admirable to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve which ſhould be longeſt and Laſt upon their Knees: the Mother ſtooping to performe her civil Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, or the Son to perform his natural and Moral Duty to his Mother. But Gods Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is above Mans, and civil Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations bind not ſo faſt, as Moral and Eternal Statutes, Impoſed by God himſelf.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="20" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:119587:34"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 20.</head>
                     <p>The Direction now given, how children ought to addreſſe to their Parents in asking bleſſing, it yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains to diſcover when, or at what times, it is proper: To this Quaere it is anſwered, that Honour and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence is always due from the children to Parents; and this they owe them, as Requiſites belonging to their Perſons, their Names, their Memories, but properly and chiefly to their Perſons. Yet this Right is moſt rationally performed, when 'tis done (if poſſible) twice a day. As God commanded a Morning and Evening Sacrifice: ſo the Parents (who bear Gods Image and Truſt) may expect the firſt fruits of their childrens duty in the Morning, and their Acknowledgement as thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Incenſe in the Evening. The Bleſsing in the Morning may cauſe a happier ſucceſs to their ſtrength, their healths, their labours, their
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:119587:35"/>ſtudies, their Lawfull deſires, and Endeavours: The Bleſſings at the Evening may be as a Seal of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents good Will, and cordial affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, liking or approving of what hath paſſed in the day. And by this means Parents and children may more ſecurely and quietly lye down, and take their Natural Repoſe; Both being firſt recommended to God in their prayers, without whoſe Bleſsing neither Relation can Reſt or ſleep in ſafety, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 127. <hi>ver.</hi> 3.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="21" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 21.</head>
                     <p>The Action and practiſe of giving and asking Bleſſing being thus War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted, yet the Ignorant Parents or unskilfull Children may demand, <hi>Quo ſtilo,</hi> in what phraſe, termes or words the Bleſſing may be craved, or Granted? (for the Relations conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue all along to both parties.) To this it may be anſwered, that the children are not ſtrictly obliged to any ſingle form, or Mode of Words;
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:119587:35"/>provided the Requeſt made by the children to their Parents in this kind be Regulated, and conſonant to the Rules and Examples of Piety, and the practiſe of Gods ſervants, whoſe lights have ſo ſhined on Earth that We beholding their good Works, may glorifie our Father which is in Heaven, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.16. To this Purpoſe, the ſons of <hi>Noah</hi> are Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terns of Modeſty, lowlineſs and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.23, 26. when they obtained the <hi>Bleſsing</hi> from their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; <hi>Iſaac</hi> of Innocency receiving the Bleſsing of his Father <hi>Abraham, Gen.</hi> 22.17. <hi>In bleſsing I will bleſſe thee, and in multiplying I will multiply thee, thy Seed ſhall be as the Stars of Heaven, and as the Sand on the Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhore: Plenty and Victory, ſhall be Iſaac's bleſsing; His ſeed ſhall poſſeſſe the Gate of his Enemies. Jacob</hi> was a great Example of Humility and O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience * in hearkning to his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers counſel for the obtaining his Father <hi>Iſaac's</hi> Bleſſing. He ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proacheth with goodly Rayment on
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:119587:36"/>his ſhoulders; (formerly his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Eſau's,</hi> as <hi>Primogenitus</hi>) but he having ſold his <hi>birthright,</hi> juſtly loſt his Fathers <hi>Bleſsing:</hi> The Scripture thereupon brandeth him to poſterity as one unthankful to God and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; (<hi>A prophane perſon, who for one Morſel of meat ſold his Birthright,</hi> Heb. 12.16.) It was an Ancient cuſtom in the Primitive Ages of the World, <hi>Primogenitos habuiſse veſtem quandam Specialem, aut Spiritualem, quam in Sacrificiis tantum induebant, e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>uſque in Solemnitatibus, &amp; Conviviis benedicere ſolitos fratribus natu mino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus, recepturos tandem Parentum be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedictionem.</hi> D. Hiero. de Authorit. Hebraeor. Scriptor. Super Geneſ. 27. &amp; Iſidor. in Geneſ. 26. ſuper illum Locum, <hi>Vende mihi Primogenita:</hi> That is, The Firſt-born did wear more coſtly Garments, a more ſpecial or Spiritual Rayment, which they did put on when they were to offer Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice; And thus accountred and attired, they uſed to bleſſe their younger Brethren, met together at
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:119587:36"/>their Solemnities and Feſtivals; And thus arrayed they prepared them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, approaching to receive their Parents Bleſſing. <hi>Jacob</hi> had likewiſe <hi>pleaſant Perfumes about his Neck,</hi> and Came with a ſweet, ſoft and humble voyce when he begged his Fathers Bleſſing. <hi>Eliſha</hi> followed <hi>Elijah</hi> with zeal, affection and Reſolution, and would not leave him untill he had bleſſed him: He craveth and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth for a double portion of <hi>Elijah's</hi> Spirit, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 2.9. And when the two Prophets were parted by the Charriot and Horſes of fire, then <hi>Eliſha</hi> cryes out more paſſionately, <hi>My father; my father, the Charriot of Iſrael and the horſmen thereof:</hi> At thoſe words the Mantle of <hi>Elijah</hi> fell, wherewith he divided the ſtreames of <hi>Jordan,</hi> and paſſed over, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 2.14. The <hi>Shunamite</hi> (her ſon being dead) came with as much haſt as humility, with as much Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity, as affliction, hoping to get a Bleſſing from the Prophet. She bended her knees, and bowed to his
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:119587:37"/>feet, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 4.27. <hi>She commanded her ſervant to ſaddle the Aſſe, and to drive on,</hi> ver. 24. <hi>and in the anguiſh of her ſoul; ſhe took an Oath and ſware, As the Lord liveth I will not leave thee until I have gained a Bleſſing for my ſon,</hi> ver. 30. The Convert <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> begging a Bleſsing from Chriſt, came with Courteſie, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting her Box of Oyntment; with modeſty, ſhe ſtood behind; with ſorrow, weeping for her ſins; with humility waſhing Chriſts feet with her Teares; with Repentance, wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping his feet with thoſe Locks that had vainly enticed others: with af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, kiſsing Chriſts feet with thoſe tender Scarlet lips, that had been formerly the deceitfull Baits of ſin, <hi>Luke</hi> 7.37, 38. Here was cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly a Broken heart, and <hi>Bended knees,</hi> and all the Teſtimonies, and Circumſtances of Humility, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence of a penitent ſinner craving pardon and a bleſsing from her Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour: Her Brackiſh Teares were her paſsionate Orators, her actions,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:119587:37"/>and affections were perſwaſive Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence to plead for her. The <hi>Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitiſh-woman</hi> came to Chriſt with out-cryes and Lamentation, and ſaid, <hi>Have mercy upon me,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Luke</hi> 15.22. At the 25. <hi>ver. ſhe fell down and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhiped him,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Lord help me;</hi> at the 27. <hi>verſe</hi> Chriſt diſcerneth her con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy, her patience, her perſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and then the bleſsing came, <hi>ver.</hi> 28. <hi>Be it unto thee as thou wilt.</hi> There is yet one Example of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility which exceedeth all others, ſet us by our Saviour, and recorded by <hi>S. Matthew</hi> 26.39. who begging a Bleſsing from his Father; humbly <hi>fell on his face and prayed,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Oh my father if it be poſsible let this Cup paſſe from me, nevertheleſſe not as I will, but as thou wilt; All theſe</hi> Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples in the Patriarchs and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, the Diſciples and Chriſt himſelf, invite us to an humble and Dutifull Style, when we make our Requeſts either for a bleſsing from God, or our Parents. And that which God requires from us in a divine
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:119587:38"/>and ſpiritual manner when we make our prayers to the Father of Lights, may be performed in a civil and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Rite, to our Parents when we crave their bleſsing. And it is St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Argument for Parents: <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.9. <hi>If Children owe their Parents ſuch Reverence and ſubjection under their Correction; with what ſubmiſſe Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, begging and entreating,</hi> With what humble Geſtures <hi>kneeling</hi> or <hi>proſtrating</hi> themſelves down to the Earth, ought they to addreſſe to their Parents, expecting their Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, their favour, their Benevolence, their Prayers to God for them, and their reconcilement to them? If theſe Examples ſeem too General, and therefore of weaker force, or leſſe obliging, as not ſtrictly direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which beſt to follow: Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren are to be inſtructed, that they are concerned as to them all, on ſeveral occaſions or reſpects, when they are to preſent their duties to their Parents. So that the modeſty of <hi>Shem</hi> and <hi>Japhet,</hi> the Innocency
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:119587:38"/>of <hi>Iſaac,</hi> the Obedience and Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiveneſſe of <hi>Jacob,</hi> the zeal and affection of <hi>Eliſha,</hi> the Importunity of the <hi>Shunamite,</hi> the paſsionate teares of <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi> the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cryes and Lamentations of the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanitiſh woman,</hi> and the humility of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> falling on his face, and praying to his Father: Theſe are all Warrantable Examples, both works, and Words teaching the phraſe, or Manner how to beg the Parents Bleſsing; This difference only firſt reſerved, God is to be Worſhiped as the Father of Spirits, Eternal and Immortal, and the Parents to be Honoured as the Fathers and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of their childrens Fleſh. God is to be called on with Faith, with a divine and ſpiritual Invocation, and the Parents are to be entreated by their children with civil and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſupplications, when they ſue to them for their bleſsings. And hereby they honour God himſelf in honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe whom he commands ſhall be honoured, by the expreſs Order and words of his Law.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="22" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 22.</head>
                     <pb n="64" facs="tcp:119587:39"/>
                     <p>Yet if all theſe Inſtances ſeem but as Lines that reſt in the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, and ſtretch not ſo far as the Center of the Point, and Argument in hand; More particularly, chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren may beg their Parents Bleſsing either <hi>per Lachrimas,</hi> by their Tears, or <hi>per Verba,</hi> by humble Words, or elſe <hi>per Signa,</hi> ſome Actions imply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and repreſenting the deſires and Affections of their hearts. And in this regard (as S. <hi>Hierom</hi> on ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther occaſion ſpeaking of the Prieſts) <hi>Omnia in Liberis debent eſſe Vocalia.</hi> All circumſtances in children ſhould be Vocal, in ſome degree or other ſpeaking forth their Duty to their parents. Thoſe who cannot ſpeak may Weep, as <hi>Mary Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalen,</hi> Luke 7.38. of whom we read not, that ſhe ſpake a Word. Little Infants (whilſt they cannot ſpeak) let them learn to lift up their hands, or teſtifie their Obedienee by ſome
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:119587:39"/>other Circumſtances, as of humbling the head, or uſing the Flexure of the Knees. This weeping is a ſilent king of Begging, this bending an an obedient ſign or Mode of entreat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Parents favour. Now, that teares have Tongues appears in King <hi>Davids</hi> phraſe; <hi>The Lord</hi> (ſaith that Royal Prophet) <hi>hath heard the voyce of my Weeping:</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>: thus the Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuagint; It may ſeem more paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionate from the Original: <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> that is, he hearkned or liſtened at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentively, or, he put his Ear into my Weeping. Parents thus touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, thus Accoſted, cannot but have compaſsion and tenderneſſe for their weeping children, though they crave not their Bleſſing by any compoſure of Words at all. There is another way of obtaining the Parents bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and that is <hi>per Signa,</hi> when the obedient children coming to their Parents on this Religious Errand or Buſineſſe, manifeſt the deſires of their hearts by ſome ſignal exteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:119587:40"/>geſtures; declaring their affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions by their Actions, and ſpeak the ſenſe of their Minds by by the humble deportment of their Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies: as it is commonly and civilly performed ſometimes by the unco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering to the head, kiſsing of the hand, moving of the Leg; ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king their honour by Courchee, and ſo bowing the Bodies, or bending the Knees: which Ceremonies if per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by Equals, whether ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintances, kindred, ſtrangers, or friends: they paſs only, and are ſo judged as meer civil Reſpects; as Familiar amongſt Heathens as Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians: But when they are ballanced and guided by the Conſcience: as actions due to the ſeveral Relations of Magiſtrates, Maſters and Parents, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>at is, Fathers and Mothers, they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> not meerly from Cuſtom or hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Civility, but from a better Foundation, that which God hath laid, on which a higher building is to be raiſed, <hi>Honour thy Father and Mother, which is the first Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:119587:40"/>with promiſe;</hi> and ſuch a one, as if not rightly obſerved will cauſe a Breach or neglect of all that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low: And it is to be feared, that he that takes the Liberty to diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour his Parents, will make little or no Conſcience whom he doth murder, from whom he Robs, whom he defileth with his Luſt, how falſe he is to his Neighbour, or how co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous of his Neighbours goods. If then Kings and Princes or Supreme Magiſtrates may expect duty and honour from their Subjects and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, not only for fear, but as charged by a conſcientious Obligation, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.3, 4, 5. <hi>not only for wrath, but for conſcience ſake,</hi> If Maſters are not only to be ſerve with <hi>eye-ſervice, but fidelity of the heart,</hi> and that their <hi>Eyes are to watch and wait on their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and Miſtreſſes buſineſs:</hi> What degrees of Duty are children to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to their Parents? in whom theſe branches of honour and Obedience to Magiſtrates and Maſters are pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marily and Originally founded.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="23" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="68" facs="tcp:119587:41"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 23.</head>
                     <p>There is yet another Way or Mode of Addreſſe to Parents <hi>per Verba,</hi> by Words; which are to be accompanyed and cloathed with hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, Reverence and Honour. And if a pious Chriſtian Cuſtom not of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending Any, (if rightly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood) nor oppoſing the Word of God, may Warrant Obedient chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren: They asking their Parents bleſſing may lawfully ſay (as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly taught by their Parents <hi>in haec Verba</hi>) I pray you Father or Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, pray to God to bleſſe me: Or as ſome others uſe it, I pray you Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or Mother Give me your Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing. Thus God himſelf directeth King <hi>Abimelech</hi> to pray to <hi>Abraham,</hi> that <hi>Abraham</hi> a Prophet might <hi>Pray</hi> for him, <hi>Gen.</hi> 20.7, 17. So <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham pray'd to God for him, and God heard his ſervant</hi> Abraham, <hi>and God healed</hi> Abimelech. <hi>Pharaoh</hi> entreat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> to pray for him,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:119587:41"/>and his plagued Countrey, <hi>Exodus</hi> 9.28. The people cryed out to <hi>Samuel,</hi> pray for thy ſervants to the Lord thy God, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.19. <hi>St. Paul</hi> puts life into this Religious Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe by his own practiſe: <hi>Precor autem Vos fratres. I beſeech you Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren for the Lord Jeſus Chriſt's ſake, and for the love of the Spirit, that you ſtrive together with me in your prayers to God for me,</hi> Rom. 15.36. <hi>Precum officium ab eis Poſtulat, ostendit quare in quibuſvis difficultatibus niti nos ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xime oporteat:</hi> Mr. <hi>Beza</hi> Commenteth thus on the Words: On ſome Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions a conjunction and Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of prayers is very Neceſſary. St. <hi>Paul</hi> was as earneſt with the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſians</hi> as the <hi>Romanes; pray for me,</hi> Epheſ. 6.19. and with the <hi>Philippi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> as the <hi>Epheſians: I know that this ſhall turn to my ſalvation through your prayer,</hi> Phil. 1.19. Thus the Apoſtle entreateth the <hi>Coloſsians,</hi> Chap. 4. verſe 3. and the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> 2 Theſ. 3.1. and the <hi>Jewes</hi> his own Nation, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.19. After this manner God
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:119587:42"/>counſelled <hi>Jobs</hi> three friends, <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phas</hi> the <hi>Temanite,</hi> and <hi>Bildad</hi> the <hi>Shuite,</hi> and <hi>Zophar</hi> the <hi>Naamathite,</hi> and commanded them, <hi>Go unto my ſervant</hi> Job <hi>and offer up for your ſelves a burnt Offering, and my ſervant</hi> Job <hi>ſhall pray for you, for him will I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept. And they did as the Lord com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them, and the Lord alſo accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> Job, <hi>and they god a Bleſsing,</hi> Job 42.8, 9, 10. Now if Kings and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple beg a bleſſing from their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Prieſts: Nay, if the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles entreat their Diſciples to pray for them: How earneſt ought children to be with their parents for their Zealous and aſſiduous prayers? to beg their Bleſſing, and to pray their parents to pray to God for his Bleſſing on them? And if the <hi>fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent prayer of a Righteous man availeth much,</hi> Certainly the affectionate de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires and prayers of tender-hearted compaſsionate parents, (whoſe bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els yearn in them for their children; either having erred ignorantly, or offended wilfully, and afterward
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:119587:42"/>repenting heartily) cannot but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive good ſucceſſe, and Grace from the Mercy-ſeat of Almighty God.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="24" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 24.</head>
                     <p>Some uſe a ſhorter ſtyle, and fold up their Duty in fewer Words, <hi>(viz.)</hi> I <hi>pray you Father or Mother give me your Bleſsing:</hi> Which Kind is as pathetical, and may prove as Effectual as the Other, there being no contradiction at all betwixt them, but only a difference, or, <hi>modus Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quendi;</hi> Importing the ſame thing: The children uſing this phraſe, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply equally as much; and when they ſay, <hi>Give your Bleſſing, it is</hi> the ſame, received by the parents, and intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the children, as, <hi>Give the Bleſsing of your prayers;</hi> give your affectionate Teſtimony towards us, or aſſure us of the Continuance of your tender care and goodneſſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us, and of our hope and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation in You.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="25" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="72" facs="tcp:119587:43"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 25.</head>
                     <p>There are yet ſome who uſe a ſhorter and more Conciſe phraſe then this Laſt: when they appear in the Dutiful addreſs of asking Bleſſing; Making the Text of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture the Warrant, the Method and matter of their pious requeſt, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no more then what <hi>Eſau</hi> did to his Father, <hi>Bleſs me, O my Father or Mother,</hi> Geneſ. 27.38. where the vulgar Latine hath it <hi>Pater mihi obſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cro ut Benedicas</hi> which importeth as much, as, I pray or beſeech you Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bleſs me: the Septuagint coming nearer to the Original, tranſlate the Words <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly rendred in the Engliſh Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, <hi>Bleſſe me, even me, O my Father,</hi> Gen. 27.38. The Patriarch <hi>Jacob</hi> uſeth the like Words craving a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing from <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and ſaying, <hi>Let my Father ariſe, and eat of his Sons Veni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, ut Benedicat mihi anima ſua:</hi> Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſ. 27.31. <hi>that his ſoul might bleſs
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:119587:43"/>me.</hi> In all theſe varieties there are differences, but not contradiction; &amp; the children being thus taught &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed by their Religious parents how, and when to ask their Bleſſing, or guided by theſe Examples of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scripture, are more exactly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected how to honour, and after what manner to crave their parents Bleſſing.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="26" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 26.</head>
                     <p>The Children being thus Inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, it will be as pertinent that the parents be adviſed how, or after what manner they are to beſtow their Bleſſing on their Obedient children. And to this Caſe it may be anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that as the children diverſificate in the manner of their Requeſts, craving the Bleſſing: to their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents may ſafely vary in the Diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution of their Benedictions, as to their phraſe, or Method of their Diſpenſations; and yet the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing be no whit leſſe in effect or O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration.
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:119587:44"/>
                        <hi>Iſaac</hi> in bleſſing his Son <hi>Jacob,</hi> prayeth to God, <hi>Deus Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potens tibi Benedicat, God Almighty</hi> Bleſſe thee and make thee fruitfull, <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 28.3. <hi>Joſeph</hi> changeth his ſtyle of Bleſſing into other Words, compoſed of the rare Ingredients of pity and piety, and bleſſed his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Benjamin,</hi> and ſaid, <hi>God be gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious to thee my Son,</hi> Geneſ. 43.29. <hi>Frater natu major minori Benedixit:</hi> Here the Elder Brother (being a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and the <hi>Aegyptians</hi>) bleſſeth the younger, according to St. <hi>Pauls</hi> ſpeech (mentioned before) <hi>the Leſse is Bleſſed of the better or greater,</hi> Heb. 7.7. There is a va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of Bleſſings recorded in the Book of <hi>Deuteronomy:</hi> when <hi>Moſes</hi>
                        <note n="*" place="margin">Moſes. v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>r Dei b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                              <desc>…</desc>
                           </gap>dixit ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                              <desc>…</desc>
                           </gap>is <hi>Iſrael</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>te <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>m <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>. <hi>Deut. 31.</hi>
                        </note> received <hi>Jacobs</hi> bleſſings on his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, bleſſed his children; Let <hi>Reuben</hi> live, <hi>Deuter.</hi> 33.6. Lord hear the voyce of <hi>Judah, ver.</hi> 7. Let thy <hi>Thummim</hi> and thy <hi>Urim</hi> be with <hi>Levi,</hi> thy holy One, <hi>ver.</hi> 8. The Lord ſhall cover <hi>Benjamin</hi> all the Day long, <hi>ver.</hi> 12. As he bleſſeth <hi>Joſeph,</hi> he pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:119587:44"/>for the good Will of him that dwelt in the <hi>Buſh,</hi> Let the Bleſsing come on the head of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the top of the head of him that was ſeparated from his Brethren, <hi>ver.</hi> 16. Let <hi>Zebulon</hi> rejoyce in his going out, and <hi>Iſſachar</hi> in his Tents, <hi>ver.</hi> 18. Bleſſed be he that enlargeth <hi>Gad; Dan</hi> is as a Lion; <hi>Nephali</hi> poſſeſs thou the Weſt and the South; let <hi>Aſher</hi> be bleſſed with children, and Dip his feet in Oyl, <hi>Deuter.</hi> 33.22, 23, 24. Here were multitudes of Bleſſings variouſly expreſſed from the Tender goodneſs of a loving and Kind Father of his people. There is yet another more exact from of Bleſſing which God taught <hi>Moſes,</hi> and <hi>Moſes</hi> taught <hi>Aaron</hi> and his ſonnes; And that continues as a Moral or Eternal Direction; teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing both <hi>Jewes</hi> and Chriſtians how the Prieſts ſhould bleſs the people, or the Parents their children; On this wiſe ſhall ye bleſs the children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſaying unto them, <hi>The Lord bleſſe thee, and keep thee, The
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:119587:45"/>Lord make his face to ſhine upon thee and be gracious unto thee; The Lord lift up his Countenance upon thee and give thee peace: and they ſhall put my Name upon the children of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>and I will bleſs them,</hi> Numbers 6.22, 23, 24, 25, 26, 27. <hi>verſes.</hi> Such Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage as this King <hi>David</hi> taught; <hi>The Bleſſing of the Lord be upon you, Pſalm</hi> 129.8. There are ſome other Circumſtances and Concomitants, which Parents uſe in the Bleſsing of their children, and their Childrens children, Beſides their Votal and Vocal Benedictions and prayers. <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> calleth for his Grandchildren, and ſaith to <hi>Joſeph, Bring them unto me and I will bleſſe them,</hi> Geneſ. 48.10. <hi>and he kiſſed them and embraced them:</hi> And <hi>Joſeph</hi> brought them out from between his Knees, and he Bowed with his face to the Earth; And <hi>Joſeph</hi> took them Both, <hi>Ephraim in his right hand, toward</hi> Iſraels <hi>left hand, and</hi> Manaſſeh <hi>in his left hand towards</hi> Iſraels <hi>right hand, and brought them near unto him; And</hi> Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:119587:45"/>
                        <hi>ſtretched out his right hand, and laid it upon</hi> Ephraims <hi>head, who was the younger, and his left hand upon</hi> Manaſſe's <hi>head, guiding his hand, wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingly; and thus he bleſſed</hi> Joſeph <hi>and his Grandchilden,</hi> Gen. 48.15, 20. Heb. 11.21. <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to Crown this Way of Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, and recommendeth it by his Example to all Ages; who at his Aſcention led his Diſciples out as far as <hi>Bethany,</hi> and <hi>he lift up his hands and bleſſed them; And it came to paſſe while he bleſſed them, he was parted from them and carried up into Heaven,</hi> Luke 24.50, 51. In this Farewell of our Saviours; three paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages are more highly remarkable: Firſt, that Chriſt led his Apoſtles <hi>to Bethany, Quae domus obedientiae dici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur;</hi> that is, as it ſignifies, to the houſe or Village of Obedience: <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t qui propter Inobedientiam perverſorum deſcenderat, propter Obedientiam Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſorum aſcenderet:</hi> That as he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended in compaſſion for thoſe who had been Diſobedient, he might
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:119587:46"/>gloriouſly aſcend for the Conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thoſe who were convered and become Obedient; ſo Venerable <hi>Bede.</hi> Secondly, when he had led his Diſciples to <hi>Bethany,</hi> he lifted up his hands; <hi>forſan vim Conſervativam influens eis uſque ad adventum Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, &amp; fortaſsis inſtruens nos, ut quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties recedimus; Benedictionibus Subdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos Deo recommendemus;</hi> Theophil. Either to influence them with a Conſervative power, and to ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then his Apoſtles untill a plenary miſſion of the holy Ghoſt: Or to inſtruct them, and others, to Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend thoſe who were Obedient Souls, to Gods Favour and further Bleſſings. Thirdly, Having led his Apoſtles to <hi>Bethany,</hi> and having lift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up his hands, he <hi>Bleſſed them: Quod autem elevatis manibus Benedixit eis, ſignificat quod deceat Benedicentem cuiquam ornatum eſſe variis Operibus, &amp; arduis, reſpectu aliorum:</hi> The Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of his hands may rightly ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie the Tranſcendent Excellency of Chriſt's perſon, in whom Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:119587:46"/>fulneſs dwelt, that he might be more able and compleat to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence and diffuſe his Heavenly Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedictions; whoſe Salutations were in peace after his Reſurrection; <hi>Peace be unto you,</hi> St. <hi>John</hi> 20.19, 21. But his Valediction were in his Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of his Diſciples at his Aſcenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, St. <hi>Luke</hi> 24.51. Theſe Examples of the Patriarch <hi>Jacob:</hi> and of Chriſt our Lord, may teach all Parents the right Rules and Method how to bleſs their children: and (if there be cauſe) to manifeſt their good Will and affections towards them, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with the Word of their Mouthes, but with the <hi>impoſition of their hands upon their childrens heads,</hi> as <hi>Jacobs</hi> were on <hi>Ephraims</hi> and <hi>Manaſſes:</hi> or with an Elevation or Expanſion of them towards heaven to beg a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing from God: and by this Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance to teach their children to be Supernal and Spiritual in their Thoughts, and more Coeleſtial in their Converſations; By admitting them to come unto them, as the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarch
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:119587:47"/>triarch <hi>Jacob</hi> called for for his Grandchildren, and then paſſionate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Kiſſed and Embraced them, and ſo bleſſed them. Yet the nhildren may not expect a Bleſſing nor the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents freely part with it, untill the children are brought to the houſe, and habit of Obedience: as Chriſt led his Diſciples firſt to <hi>Bethany,</hi> and then bleſſed them.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="27" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 27.</head>
                     <p>There is yet an Objection to be removed out of the Way, which may ſeem in ſome degree to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt the practice of this Affectionate and Religious Duty; raiſed from the Conceipt, that the Patriarchs ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther gave their Bleſſings as Prophets, then as Parents: and that the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings were pronounced rather out of prophetical praeviſion, then out of parental and fatherly Affection. To this it is eaſily Anſwered, The Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarchs are to be conſidered as to both Relations: firſt as Prophets,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:119587:47"/>who ſpake of old as they were inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the Holy Ghoſt, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.21: and in this Reſpect, by Inſpirations, Viſions, &amp; Revelations they did fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell, inſtruct, &amp; acquaint their poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties what Bleſſings were likely to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low them or fall upon them. Secondly, The Patriarchs are to be looked up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as Parents, Fathers, Mothers, Grandfathers or Grandmothers, or other Superiour degrees in Conſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinity and Blood; and in this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation the Parents Bleſsing rather riſeth from Affection, then Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and rather from the force of tender and natural Love, then the Spirit of propheſie: which although they differ in their Subjects, (pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie looking only after that which is <hi>Verum,</hi> Truth, and the affections of the Parents only looking and long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after that which is <hi>Bonum</hi> good for his Child,) yet it is not incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent but that a divine Prophet may be a tender Parent, and as well impart his Bleſſings to Obedient children, as to Reveal, and Foretell
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:119587:48"/>to them Gods good pleaſure con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning them and their poſterities, and their future Condition. And it is as true, that Parents (though no Prophets) may (as warranted by the Rules and Examples of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures) Bleſſe their dutifull children. To this purpoſe it is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved of <hi>Jacob</hi> Bleſsing the twelve Tribes, <hi>Geneſis</hi> 48.15. <hi>Jacob bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicit filiis</hi> Joſeph, <hi>hoc est, oratione Precatur eis benedictionem divinam, &amp; Conferri eis Corporalia ſimul &amp; Spiritualia Bona;</hi> as <hi>Marlorat</hi> hath it on that action of <hi>Jacobs:</hi> that is, The Patriarch Bleſſing his Sonnes and Grandſons, did not only pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie and foretell, but paſſionately did pray for a divine Benediction on his children, and begged of God temporal and Spiritual Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions for them. So then not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prophetical, but all Natural Chriſtian parents may, and ought (on juſt occaſions) to pray for Gods Bleſſing on their poſterities, and their Childrens children; The one being
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:119587:48"/>only the impulſe and Motion of Gods holy Spirit, and extraordinary, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther being the fruits of Natural and tender affection guided by the Word of God, and ſo directed to a more holy End: and which freely and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally ſtreaming from the head or Fountain cannot ſtop nor ſtay, but if interrupted, ſpeedily ſwelleth; or like an Inundation ſpreadeth and overfloweth; &amp; the natural Channel being ſtopped or dammed up caſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly falleth into ſome other obvious Courſe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="28" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 28.</head>
                     <p>Theſe things conſidered, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents ought to be exceeding Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious how, or what they teach their children, and what they practiſe on this Account; <hi>(viz.)</hi> that the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarchs gave their Bleſsings not meerly, and only as Parents, but as Prophets: For, miſ-guided by ſuch miſtakes, God may be diſhonoured, the children unbleſſed, and the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents (guilty both of the Breach of
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:119587:49"/>Gods Law, and the childrens miſery and unhappineſs) lyable to a more ſad and heavy account: and the Links and Bands of theſe near Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations once Crack't or Broken, great miſchiefs may enſue, which no Art can cure, nor Reaſon or Counſel ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and repair. St. <hi>Paul</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to bind this Cord the faſter, and that the natural Affections and inclinations of Parents might meet with no Obſtruction, teacheth the parents their Duty, as well as their children, theirs. It is true, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle firſt beginneth with the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, commanding them, <hi>Children obey your Parents in the Lord,</hi> Epheſ. 6.1. This precept is corrobora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with a three-fold Argument: Firſt, <hi>quia Deus ſic ſancivit,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God hath ſo Ordained. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, <hi>Juſtiſſima eſt haec Obedientia, &amp; rationi conſentanea,</hi> this Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is juſt and moſt agreeable to Nature and Reaſon. Thirdly, <hi>ab utili,</hi> this Duty is the better to be obſerved becauſe of the bleſsing
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:119587:49"/>and advantage Got by it, <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus hoc Praeceptum inter caetera pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiari benedictione dignatus eſt,</hi> ſaith Mr. <hi>Beza, ut bene tibi ſi t, that it may be Well with thee, and that thou mayſt live long upon the Earth,</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſ. 6.3.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="29" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 29.</head>
                     <p>The Apoſtle having firſt taught the Children, undertaketh the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, and as ſtrictly chargeth them: <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, that is, <hi>And ye Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers provoke not your children:</hi> as if the Apoſtle ſhould have ſaid, Be not over ſevere, harſh, Tyrannical and Cruel: for they are your chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, not your ſlaves; your Sonnes and Daughters, and not your Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects: made yours and to be kept yours, not only by a civil Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pact, but a Moral and Natural Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation. And there might be ſome danger, leaſt, if the Children ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve their parents not enclined to give them their Bleſſing, they may
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:119587:50"/>unreverently neglect to give that Honour that is due to their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, and ſo (eaſily tempted with ſtubborn pride) refuſe to Bow or Beg their Parents Bleſsing. The Apoſtle conſidered this Duty of the Parents to be ſo neceſſary, that he gives the like Canon to the <hi>Coloſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> as he did to the <hi>Epheſians;</hi> only changeth <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.4. into <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, the firſt tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated ne <hi>Provocate,</hi> provoke not, the latter ne <hi>irritate,</hi> do not ſtir up or Irritate, or provoke not to Anger or Vexation. On both which pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces it is obſerved, <hi>Patrum officium eſt; moderate, &amp; ad Dei gloriam jure patriae poteſtatis <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ti,</hi> that is, It is the Fathers Duty to exerciſe his paternal power with Moderation, Prudence and Diſcretion, that God may be the more Glorified. <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiritur ut parentes in liberos ſint be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nigni:</hi> It is required that Parents be Courteous, and tender towards their Obedient children. And it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>fallible truth, where the
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:119587:50"/>Golden Reciprocal Union of parents bleſsing their children, and the children Honouring their Parents is conſtantly kept and obſerved; there cannot but be length of Happy dayes, or ſuch as Lead to Immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table and Eternal Happineſſe in Heaven. On the contrary, where the Parents forgetting all Natural Affection, are over bitter, harſh, and Tyrannical to their Children; they convert Honour to Neglect, Obedience to ſturdineſſe, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, and Love into hatred, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt and ſcorn. And though the Parents on no occaſion or provoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion whatſoever are to be requited with ſuch unnatural Taunts and returnes: Yet theſe are the Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar and common Effects of incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionate neglect, or injuſt, impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and Imprudent provocations; And from hence it proves often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, that where the Parents ought to place and expect their greateſt Joy and Solace; even from thence, even from their own Bowels, they
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:119587:51"/>reap and gather the ſad Harveſts of their owne occaſioned Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="30" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 30.</head>
                     <p>But the Sin of provocation in Parents is more Rare and leſſe fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, by Reaſon that God and Nature incline the parents hearts to Kindneſſe and Compaſſion towards their children; And Love Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally deſcends and looks down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. The more dangerous and ſpreading ſin is Diſobedience in children, who (though never provok<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at all) know too well, and learn too ſodenly, by naturall depravati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to offend, diſhonour and Diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey their Loving and compaſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate parents: And from this Root ſpring up many Shoots and bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Impiety, which, in conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, occaſion much miſchief, and much miſery, often attended with Temporal, Spiritual &amp; Aeternal ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledictions
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:119587:51"/>ledictions and Curſes. <hi>Cham</hi> and his poſterity are miſerable &amp; ſad Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Gods Judgements in this Kind. The Scripture only tells, that <hi>Ham</hi> the Father of <hi>Canaan</hi> ſaw the Nakedneſſe of his Father, and told his two Brethren without, <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſis</hi> 9.22. The Sin of his diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience is not more largely deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, but rather gently remembred, then freely opened. <hi>Moſes</hi> record<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that <hi>Cham ſaw his fathers Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, and did not cover it,</hi> or, he did not only ſee with his Eyes, but talk with his Tongue, <hi>he told his two Brethren without.</hi> At the firſt ſight: this ſin of <hi>Chams</hi> ſeems to be but of a leſſer ſize; yet it appears that God was ſo highly offended at it, that it forced a curſe to fall on <hi>Cham</hi> and <hi>Canaan</hi> and their ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding generations. For, whether it be conſtrued a propheſie, or a Fathers Wiſh and Imprecation; in both kinds it is very terrible. And <hi>Noah awoke from his wine, and knew what his younger ſonne had done unto
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:119587:52"/>him, and he ſaid, curſed be</hi> Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, <hi>a ſervant of ſervants ſhall he be to his Brethren.</hi> In which Words, undoubtedly the Mouth of <hi>Noah,</hi> and the pen of <hi>Moſes</hi> (who wrote the Hiſtory) were guided directly by the Spirit of God. Who, to declare his Odium to the ſinne of Diſobedience in children, maketh <hi>Cham</hi> and his poſterity ſad and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable Spectacles to all future A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the World. The Curſe was not only denounced and inflicted on <hi>Cham,</hi> but the Lord doth long before point out as it were with his Finger where, and how this plague ſhould burn in the Houſe of <hi>Cham;</hi> whoſe children and Generations being both <hi>Aegyptians,</hi> Geneſ. 12.15. and <hi>Aethiopians,</hi> Geneſ. 10.8, 9, 10. and <hi>Canaanites,</hi> Numbers 13.28. Geneſ. 15.16. They and their Childrens children felt the bitter ſmart of this plague and Curſe for diſhonour and Diſobedience to pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents. And, what condition can be more miſerable for children,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:119587:52"/>then to be in the Scorn and Curſe of their Parents who begat them, who bred them, and would care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and tenderly provide for them, if they had but the Grace and Goodneſſed to Honour and obey them as God commands. And it is for the ſin of Diſobedience and Undu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifulneſſe, that children prove their Parents greateſt Croſſes and Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, and moſt Inſupportable Grief. Thus <hi>David</hi> was afflicted and forced to complain of <hi>Abſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom,</hi> 2 Sam. 16.11. Lamenting his condition to <hi>Abiſhai,</hi> and to all his Servants: <hi>Behold my Son which came forth of my Bowels ſeeketh my life.</hi> This Dart pierced more ſharply, wounded more deeply then all the poyſoned arrowes of his Enemies; in ſo much that the King extenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ates <hi>Shimei</hi> his curſings and Rail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, as more tolerable; becauſe ſuch high Rebellion and Diſobedience roſe from <hi>Abſalom Davids</hi> darling, and the fruit of his own Bowels. It was from hence that this great
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:119587:53"/>worthy, Renowned Champion, (though in other Rencounters of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible Courage) yet, Alarm'd by his Sons diſloyal Apoſtacy, and Diſobedient Conſpiracy, a pannick fear poſſeſſeth his Royal Soul, and the Meſſenger had no ſooner told the Newes, that the hearts of the men of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were after <hi>Abſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom,</hi> but incontinently without fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther debate or Counſel, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.13. <hi>the King quitted his Hold of</hi> Zion, <hi>and his Royal City, ſaying to his ſervants that were with him at</hi> Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, <hi>Ariſe, let us flee, for we ſhall not elſe Eſcape from</hi> Abſalom: <hi>make ſpeed to depart, leaſt he over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take us ſodainly, and being evil upon us, ſmite the City with the Edge of the Sword.</hi> It was the Diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of this Undutifull Sonne that forced more teares from his Fathers Eyes, more ſighs and Sobs from his Fathers heart, then all his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies: In all his Enterpriſes, the King with his Attendants and Guards were never in ſuch a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:119587:53"/>as was occaſioned by this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall provocation. The Story is moſt pathetical in the ſecond of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel,</hi> 15.30. <hi>And</hi> David <hi>went up by the aſcent of Mount</hi> Olivet, <hi>and wept as he went up barefoot, and all the people that were with him covered every man his head, and they went up, weeping as they went up: Every Word doth Emphaſis</hi> Grief, and Eccho Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grett: repreſent rather a Tragedy already acted, then an Enemy to be Attacqued; rather a Funeral ſolemnized then a Battel to be fought: Covering of the head, Weeping, and Walking barefoot, being rather Emblems of grief, then preparations to fight, kill, or conquer. But, ſee what ſtrange Convulſions a Diſobedient ſon for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth into the heart of a tender and compaſſionate Father! What a Tempeſt was ſuddenly raiſed in <hi>Davids</hi> Soul by the Breath of an undutifull child! and how Reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe the Fathers Spirit was, toſſed with the Billowes of fear, care,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:119587:54"/>Love and grief: conſidering that his own ſafety and his ſonnes were not conſiſtent: that the Killing of his Enemy muſt be the ſlaying of his Sonne; that the ſubduing of the Rebels muſt be the Deſtruction of his Subjects; That his Victories muſt be raiſed by the fall of him, for whom his Bowels did Yearn, and had moſt affection; or by the Death of ſome ſeduced and ſtray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſheep, deluded by fair words, &amp; ſweet Baits; for whom their true Paſtour and Prince had the Deſignes of clemency, pardon and gracious compaſſion: This was very Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in the Kings pleaſure or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, who charged his three Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals, <hi>Joab, Abiſhai and Ittai,</hi> 2 Sam. 18.2, 5. <hi>Deal gently for my ſake with the young man, even</hi> Abſalom <hi>my Son;</hi> Of whoſe death when the King received Newes from <hi>Cuſhi;</hi> 2 Sam. 18.33. he was much mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and as overflowed with an Inundation of Grief; <hi>he went up to the Chamber over the Gate, and
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:119587:54"/>Wept, &amp; as he went thus he ſaid, O my ſon</hi> Abſalom, <hi>my ſon, my ſon</hi> Abſalom, <hi>would God I had died for thee, Oh</hi> Abſalom <hi>my Son, my Son.</hi> By theſe Examples and ſad Effects, it is very eaſie to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern the unpleaſant Fruits that ſtubborn and Diſobedient children occaſion and produce to their grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and Afflicted Parents. But as to themſelves their ſinnes may prove much more dangerous and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable; for, whilſt by their wilfull Diſobedience, their ſcorn and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, they cauſe their Parents faces to Wither, their Cheeks to furrow, their Hearts to ake, and their Eyes to weep, and (in conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion) ſooner haſten their Gray Head to lie on a cold clod in their Graves; they may in the mean time haſten heavy Judgements to fall on them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; and after a ſhort life of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience and unrepented Sinnes; hurry, and haſten themſelves to Hell. As then the love of Gods favour and Bleſsing, and the Hopes of a Gracious promiſe, ſhould in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:119587:55"/>children to be Gracious, Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull and Obedient; ſo ſhould the Terrours of Gods Threats, and the Vengeance of his Juſtice; with the fearfull Execution of many heavy plagues and puniſhments, teach and perſwade children to take heed of the horrid ſinne of unworthy and unnatural Diſobedience.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="31" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 31.</head>
                     <p>It was pride and Diſobedience that was the Cauſe,<note n="*" place="margin">Epiſt. St. <hi>Jude ver.</hi> 6.</note> of <hi>Lucifers</hi> fall; and this ſinne ſuffered not <hi>Elyes</hi> undutifull Sonnes, <hi>Hophni</hi> and <hi>Phineas to live out half their dayes, but they were ſlain with the ſword,</hi> 1 Sam. 4.11. According to Gods Law, <hi>Deuter.</hi> 21.18, 19, 20, 21. <hi>If a man have a Rebellious ſon,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Judicial Law.</note>
                        <hi>which will not obey the voyce of his Father, or the voyce of his Mother, and when they have chaſtened him he will not hearken to them: Then ſhall his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and his Mother lay hold of him,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:119587:55"/>and bring him out to the Elders of the City, and to the Gate of his Place: And they ſhall ſay to the Elders of the City: This our Sonne is ſtubborn and rebellious: he will not obey our voyce, he is a Glutton and a drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kard: and all the men of the City ſhall ſtone him with stones untill he Die: ſo ſhalt thou put the Evil from among you; and all</hi> Iſrael <hi>ſhall hear and fear. The Judgements of God thus threatned againſt undutifull and Rebellious children,</hi> cannot but ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie the hearts of all who have Natural good diſpoſitions, or any ſpark of Grace: to be of more meek, ſweet and pious Tempers and humble Behaviours towards their Parents: of which heavenly Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portment Chriſt our Saviour was pleaſed to be a Bleſſed Copy and Example to his Church. Thus St. <hi>Luke</hi> writeth, <hi>Luke</hi> 2.57. <hi>He went down to</hi> Nazareth <hi>with his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, and was ſubject to them:</hi> and 'tis true, <hi>Omnis Actio Chriſti eſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructio
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:119587:56"/>Chriſtiani.</hi> Chriſts Actions are our beſt Inſtructions: and St. <hi>Hierom</hi> ſpeaks aptly to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, <hi>Chriſtus venerabatur matrem, colebat nutricium.</hi> Hieron. Epiſt. de vit and. Suſp. Connub. He Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verenced his Mother as her Son, and Honoured <hi>Joſeph</hi> his ſuppoſed Father, uſing (as many Learned Authors affirm) and exerciſing Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lial and oeconomicall Duties in their Houſe untill the Thirtieth Year of his Age. Where Chriſt is the Example: Let no Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an child refuſe to follow the Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern of his Obedience, nor vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly think his Subjection to his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents (as too many do) <hi>infirmita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis ſed pietatis officium,</hi> to be a Duty of Infirmity, but of Pietie. <hi>Amb. in Luc. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. It is the Judgement of a Lord Biſhop, and late more eminent Light of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that the Tenth or laſt Commandement is the Fountain from whence all the
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:119587:56"/>reſt of the ſecond Table do pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, as the ſtreams from the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duit Head; and the ſtreames ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit a ſecond diviſion: for, they either equally and generally reflect on all, as being our Neighbours; as the five laſt; or elſe are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to a more particular and reſtrict Relation as the fifth, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour thy Father and Mother, as from whom thou haſt (by Gods order and permiſſion) thy very Eſſence and Being. Biſhop <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drews</hi> Expoſition on the fifth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, where the ſame Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor Collecteth from <hi>Philo,</hi> that <hi>Honour</hi> due to Parents is prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red before all other Duties due to Men; and it is placed as it were <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> in Confinio, in the Confines of a Mortal, and an Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Nature; in the Middle of the firſt and ſecond Table; for, take away this one Duty of the childrens Honouring and Obeying their Parents, and then all Duties
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:119587:57"/>to God, and man will ſpeedily Ceaſe and fall to the Ground. This is due to them not only as a Reward of Excellency, the proper Object of Honour, (as the Schooles ſpeak) but it is to be tendred and given to Parents though they be Aged, Ignorant, infirm or Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent; The duty of this Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement being not directed in the Word <hi>Dilige</hi> love, but <hi>Honora,</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour thou.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="32" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 32.</head>
                     <p>If there be any nice Stomach that will not digeſt this Meat, or will cavil at this Duty, pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Scripture for their Warrant; Objecting, that None is to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Father on Earth, much leſſe Honoured as Father, from thoſe Words, <hi>Matthew</hi> 23.9. It is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, that properly, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Rules of Divinity it is
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:119587:57"/>true, There is no other Father but God; for other Parents are, as the Heathen ſay, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>: the Inſtruments of Generation un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der God; and therefore Paterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty being aſcribed both to God and Man: It is in God Originally, and properly, and in man deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatively and inſtrumentally: as it may be ſeen in the Words of the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> who makes God the firſt Father, <hi>of whom the whole Family in Heaven and Earth is Named,</hi> Epheſ. 3.17. as he is the firſt, ſo he is the laſt: So <hi>David, When my Father and Mother forſake me, the Lord taketh me up,</hi> Pſalm 27.16. Now, if all paternity or Fatherhood be derived from God to men, who be Fathers by parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipation: Their Merit, or what is due to them, ſignified in the Name <hi>[Father]</hi> muſt be drawn from God who is the Fountain of that <hi>Honour,</hi> that falleth and flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth from <hi>Fathers.</hi> There is yet
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:119587:58"/>ſomething in the very Word in the Original, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, Father, which is derived, as Biſhop <hi>Andrews</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives, from <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> to will and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, becauſe of that tender and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectionate deſire that Parents have of their childrens good. Thus <hi>Job</hi> was <hi>Pater Pauperum,</hi> Job 29.16. And was the Father hath a ſignificant Name from the Hebrew; ſo hath the Mother from the Greek Language, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>quaero vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menter, quia victum partui quaerit,</hi> becauſe ſhe ſeeks to be a preſerver of her Children. And this was one end of her Creation, to be a Helper, not only to her Husband, but to her children. So then, the very Terms of <hi>Father</hi> and <hi>Mother</hi> may moſt juſtly force and require a Duty of <hi>Honour</hi> from their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. As the Termes and Names of <hi>Father</hi> and <hi>Mother</hi> preſent the Excellency of thoſe near Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: ſo the Duty commanded is preſſed in a word of equal ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation.
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:119587:58"/>The Hebrew <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> which is tranſlated to <hi>Honour,</hi> doth firſt ſignifie to be heavy, or make hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy: <hi>Grave eſſe,</hi> aut <hi>aggravare;</hi> and by a Metaphor it is uſed for Honour: Becauſe as Gold and Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the more weighty they are, the more they are of price and Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue; Thus our Parents as the moſt precious Relations, merit the chiefeſt Honour and higheſt Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luation from their children. As the Hebrew, ſo the Greek Word hath as Emphatical a ſignificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to oblige the children to their Duty, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, Honour ſeems to have a derivation from <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>pendo,</hi> to weigh, prize, and eſteem; And theſe two words are commonly uſed by <hi>Solon, Plato,</hi> and the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Legiſlators,</hi> requiring Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the Lawes; Thus <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> are the ſame with <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> Ariſt. Pol. lib. 3. cap. 17. Et lib. 5. cap. 6. Whether then the Termes of <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi>
                        <pb n="104" facs="tcp:119587:59"/>and <hi>Mother,</hi> or the Duty of <hi>Honour</hi> be conſidered, it is very important, and moſt ſignificant; that as Care, Tenderneſſe, Love, Proviſion, Education, and Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance is due from Parents: ſo on the other part Honour, Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, a Submiſſive Gratitude, and humble deportment in Word and Deed is due to the tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted Parents: And what Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture more preſenteth Honour in Approaches; then Uncovering the head, bowing of the Body, or bending of the Knees? And what Words can ſo ſuddenly Conquer compaſſionate Parents, as when they hear their children praying; and ſee them humbly begging their Bleſsing on their Knees? This Way is ſo facile ad eaſie, that it often Molifies the Rockie diſpoſition of hard-hearted Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, who, provoked to Wrath and Unkindneſſe by ſtubborn Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience, are converted, and
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:119587:59"/>in a Moment changed to ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, tenderneſſe and Love, by the Earneſt Prayers and humble Geſtures of Relenting and Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent children. It were pity then, nay, a great and Imprudent Abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity (if not an Impiety) that this Duty ſhould not be uſed amongſt Chriſtians, which is in it ſelf ſo Innocent, to the Relations ſo Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable, and by the Word of God, and holy Examples, ſo Lawfull and Warrantable. The Sonne of <hi>Sirach,</hi> *: doth both Counſell and Countenance the whole Diſcourſe with many Evin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing Arguments, and powerfull perſwaſions, directing his Sonne, and telling him:<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Eceſiaſti.</hi> 2.3.</note>
                        <hi>The Lord hath given the Father Honour over the children,</hi> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
                        <hi>and hath canfirmed the Authority of the Mother over the ſonne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>;</hi> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> 
                        <hi>whoſo honoureth his Father ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth an Attonement for his ſins;</hi> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> 
                        <hi>And he that honoureth his Mother,</hi> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> 
                        <hi>is
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:119587:60"/>as one that layeth up Treaſure; Whoſo honoureth his Father, ſhall have joy of his own children; and when he maketh his prayer he ſhall be heard: he that Honoureth his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall have long life, and he that is Obedient to the Lord, will be a comfort to his Mother: He that feareth the Lord will Honour his father,</hi> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> 
                        <hi>and will do ſervice un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Parents as to his Maſters: Honour thy Father and Mother both in word and deed,</hi> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> 
                        <hi>that a Bleſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing may come upon thee from them; for the bleſſing of the Father E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stabliſheth the Houſes of Children,</hi> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> 
                        <hi>but the Curſe of the Mother root<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth out Foundations: Glory not in the diſhonour of thy Father:</hi> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> 
                        <hi>for thy Fathers diſhonour is no glory un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, for the glory of a man is from the honour of his Father and a Mother in diſhonour is a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach unto the children.</hi> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="15"/> 
                        <hi>My ſon, help thy Father in his Age, and
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:119587:60"/>grieve him not as long as he li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth. And if his understanding fail, have patience with him and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe him not when thou art in thy full ſtrength, for the Relieving of thy Father ſhall not be forgotten, and in ſtead of ſinnes it ſhall be added to build thee up. In the day of thine affliction it ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred; thy ſinnes ſhall melt away as the Ice in the fair warm Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. He that forſaketh his Father is as a bleſphemer, and he that angreth his Mother is Curſed of God.</hi> It is facile and eaſie to Collect and Conclude from this divine Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellour, that an Attonement for ſinnes is made; that a Treaſure is laid up; That Joy is added: Prayers are heard; Long life is procured; Houſes are Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and built up: Afflictions re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred, and ſinnes are made to melt away as the Ice in the fair warm weather; When Children
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:119587:61"/>rightly pay and render that Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, Duty, Reverence, and Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to their Parents, which God commandeth.</p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:119587:61" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>'ΕΥΔΟΧΙΑ.</p>
                  <p>A Model of private Prayers: OR, Occaſional Helps in Retired Devotions.</p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Damaſc.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Compoſed by <hi>Edward Wolley,</hi> D. D. Chaplain in Ordinary to his Majeſty.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. R.</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>William Palmer,</hi> at the ſign of the <hi>Palm-tree</hi> in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet,</hi> and at the <hi>Gun</hi> in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1661.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayers">
                  <pb facs="tcp:119587:62"/>
                  <p>'ΕΥΔΟΧΙΑ.</p>
                  <p>A Model of private Prayers, OR, Occaſional Helps in Retired Devotions.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Creed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I believe in God the Father Almighty, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Lords Prayer,</hi> Our Father which art in Heaven, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:119587:62"/>
                  <head>TO THE Kings moſ Excellent MAJESTY; <hi>Charles,</hi> by the Grace of GOD, King of <hi>England, Scotland, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> Defender of the Faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Od hath made your Majeſtie not only a King, but <hi>Pater Patriae;</hi> the Father of all your King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes and Countries. In this Reflexion All your Subjects owe
<pb facs="tcp:119587:63"/>you Loyaltie and Allegiance, and are (as dutifull Children) to render Honour and obedience to your Sacred Perſon and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands; They are (on all juſt grounds) to ſupply your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie with Support and Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and to adventure, and hazard their deareſt lives and richeſt Fortunes in the Defence of your Royal Crown and Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie. This Truth hath been Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in the blood of many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Loyal Subjects of your three Kingdomes, who in your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties, and in your Royal Fathers Service of the Wars, choſe rather to loſe their lives, then their Loyaltie. Thus whileſt others of looſer Principles ſtarted from their Duty; your Loyal-hearted
<pb facs="tcp:119587:63"/>People, as obedient Children, were faithfull to the Death, and the vigour of their Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions was (Probably) raiſed from the ſure Foundations of Pietie, and Gods holie Law, which commandeth <hi>jure poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivo</hi> Honour thy Father and thy Mother. And had this Moral dutie been well taught, and well learn't: It is very Poſſible this latter Age had not produced ſuch Black Rebellion; but that the Church might have had better Chriſtians, your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie better ſubjects, Maſters better ſervants, and Parents more obedient Children. To meliorate all which Relations, this Manual adventures into the World under the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mbrage of
<pb facs="tcp:119587:64"/>your Majeſties Grace and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, which hath encouraged the Endeavours of</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Majeſties Devoted and obedient Subject and Chaplain E. WOLLEY.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:119587:64"/>
                  <head>To the READER.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Model or Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuel of private prayers is adjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents Bleſſings, the rather, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it aymeth chiefly, at the begetting of true Honour and Obedience to all Superiours, whether Spiritual, or Civil, or Natural: And what help ſo good, what ayre ſo ſweet, or Soares ſo high, as the breath and perfume of holy and true
<pb facs="tcp:119587:65"/>Devotion, which reacheth, and is quickly elevated from the Altar of an humble heart to the Throne of God; yet it is poſſible that good affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons may want expreſſions, And weak and wandring Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellers require a Guide; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially after the diſmall ſtormes of a bloody civil War, and the confuſions and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractions produced by that ugly Monſter. But now the tempeſt being over (thanks and praiſe to Almighty God) it may be ſeaſonable to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to ſettle the minds of many: who, as Paſſengers at Sea, have had their conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſhipwracked for many yeares, or carried away with
<pb facs="tcp:119587:65"/>the puffs of ſtrange Doctrine; And to refreſh others, who have felt their ſhare in the late bitter ſtormes, and are not yet ſecurely Return'd into the Haven, where their ſouls may be at reſt; to rectifie whoſe ſtomachs, and comfort whoſe ſpirits nothing Can be more Cordial and proper, then Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate and Publick Prayer.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>Farewell.</salute>
                  </closer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:119587:66"/>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119587:66"/>
                  <div n="king" type="prayer">
                     <head>A Prayer for a King, or a Soveraign Prince.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Moſt Gracious Lord, who in great favour and mercy haſt ſet a Crown of pure Gold upon my head, and a Royal Scepter in may hand;<note place="margin">Pſalm 21.</note> and haſt girded me with a ſword of Power: make my honour great in thy Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; Prevent me ſtill with the bleſsings of goodneſſe: keep my hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t upright in thy ſervice, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer not evil Counſel to Approach near mine Eares, Nor wicked Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples to preſent themſelves be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mine eyes: Let not Lyars abuſe Truth, nor Flatterers corrupt or Alienate my Love fromt it.<note place="margin">Pſal. 101.</note> Streng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:119587:67"/>then my Reſolutions againſt proud looks and high ſtomachs, that I may not ſuffer them, nor deceitfull per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſons to dwell in my Houſe, or thoſe who tell Lies to tarry in my ſight: Continue me a Nurſing-father to thy Church, and a true Defender of the Faith; A graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Soveraign to all my Subjects: And that all my thoughts, Words and Actions may be ſo ſeaſoned with Grace, and the fear of God, that my eyes may look unto ſuch as be faithfull in the Land, and that they may dwell with me: And that thoſe who lead a Godly life may be my ſervants. Above all things, let me have Underſtanding in the way of Godlineſſe, that I may walk in thy Houſe with a perfect heart; And let Juſtice ſit with me on my Throne, and Prudence with me at my Counſels: Let Temperance be my Companion, and Fortitude my Encouragement, and ſo adorn my ſoul with Moral Vertue and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly graces: That whilſt I live on
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:119587:67"/>Earth I may ſtill grow in favour with God and man: and when I ſhall be diſſolved from my earthly Tabernacle, I may receive an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Crown of Glory: and all for Jeſus Chriſts ſake our Lord and Saviour. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="subjects" type="prayer">
                     <head>The Subjects Prayer.</head>
                     <p>ALmighty Lord, who Art the God of Order, and not the Author of Confuſion; Give me grace to reflect on my own condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and to know my ſelf that I may the better perform my Duty to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God and towards man. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue my heart Loyal faithfull and Obedient to my Soveraign, and make me dutiful and ſubmiſſive to the Lawes. Let neither Ambition nor covetouſneſſe tempt my ſoul to ſin, nor Rebellion bewitch and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnare my affections from my Prince; Give me grace ever chearfully to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119587:68"/>Render unto <hi>Caeſar</hi> thoſe things which are <hi>Caeſars:</hi> and to God thoſe things which are Gods: that I may live and proſper under a happy Government, and end my dayes in peace and the quiet of a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience: and ſo may be in the End Eternally bleſſed, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="commanders" type="prayer">
                     <head>The Captaines or Commanders Prayer.</head>
                     <p>ALmighty God, who art King of Kings and Lord of Hoſts: and commandeſt all things both in Heaven and Earth, make me truly Zealous and couragious in a good cauſe. Let neither Death nor dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger terrifie my ſoul from thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, nor the force and rage of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies affright my Reſolutions: pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve my heart in obedience to my Superiours, and make them willing, chearful &amp; ſucceſsful whom I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand:
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119587:68"/>Cover my head in the day Battel, and let me dwell under the defence of the moſt High: ſuffer me not to be afraid of any terrour by night, or for the Arrow that flyeth by day; Give thy holy Angels charge over me to keep me in all my wayes, And as a good Centuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, let Faith be my ſhield, Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe my Breſt-plate, Hope my Helmet, a good conſcience my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rade and companion: That thus ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and fighting with the ſword of the Spirit, I may gain Victory o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all my Enemies: and in the End may reſt in Peace and Triumph in glory, with Jeſus Chriſt my Lord and Saviour. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="private soldiers" type="prayer">
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:119587:69"/>
                     <head>The Private ſoldiers Prayer.</head>
                     <p>MOſt gracious and mercifull Lord, look favourably on me thy poor ſervant, let thy glory be the ground of my encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and a good cauſe only oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion my feet to march, and my hands to fight; make me truly Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant in the day of battel, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve me from death and danger; Arm me with patience in diſtreſſe, and with Reſolutions of Fidelity in thy honour and ſervice: let neither a Babyloniſh garment nor a wedg of Gold, unjuſtly tempt my affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, nor power and ſucceſſe make me fierce and cruel; let not plenty Lull me in ſecurity, nor drown me in debauched intemperance; and let not Victory encline me to pride or inſolency, direct me that I may do violence to no man: Neither ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe any falſely, and to be contented with my wages: And ſo diſpoſe of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:119587:69"/>me in all my Thoughts, words and deeds, that in Peace and War, in life and death, I may have the joy and comfort of a good conſcience: And all this I humbly crave for Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſts ſake my Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="masters" type="prayer">
                     <head>The Maſters Prayer.</head>
                     <p>MOſt bleſſed Lord, who doeſt Rule and govern all things: I beſeech thee that I may walk humbly before thee, with a perfect and upright heart in my Vocation and Calling: keep my lips from fraud and guile, and my hands from unjuſt dealings: Let my converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be juſt and innoent towards God and towards man; give a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to my endeavours, and proſper the works and labours of my hands: ſuffer me not to be harſh or bitter to thoſe that ſerve me, nor to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>civil to my Neighbours, Let truth
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:119587:70"/>and honeſty keep me company, and a good conſcience be my compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion day and night: And ſo direct the whole Race and courſe of my life that I may live all my daies in thy fear, and die in thy favour and love, for Jeſus Chriſts ſake my bleſſed Saviour and Redeemer. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="servants" type="prayer">
                     <head>The Servants Prayer.</head>
                     <p>HOlie, Righteous and bleſſed Lord, who doſt preſerve and provide for thoſe that truſt in thee, look graciouſlie on the thine un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy ſervant, Let thy fear dwell ever in my heart, and the honour of thy bleſſed Name inflame my ſoul with love of thee; keep my thoughts from Temptation to evil, my hands from fraud and deceit, from picking, Purloyning or ſtealing; Reſtrain my tongue from curſing, ſwearing or blaſpheming, and from evil ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:119587:70"/>lying and ſlandering good Lord deliver me; let Diligence and O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to juſt commands, make me to delight in my Emploiments, and to add a chearfulneſſe to my ſervice, make me ſincere to my Maſters truſt, and to perform the Duty of my place with fear and trembling in ſingleneſſe of heart, as unto Chriſt; Not with Eie-ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, as a man-pleaſer, but as a ſervant of Chriſt doing the Will of God from the heart. And that all things under my care may proſper and have better ſucceſſe; Influence the Graces of thy Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Spirit upon my ſoul, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing guided by thee I may ever ſerve thee in Righteouſneſſe and true holineſſe through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="guardians" type="prayer">
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:119587:71"/>
                     <head>The Guardians Prayers.</head>
                     <p>O Lord who art the God of Truth, and ſeeſt and ſearcheſt the hearts of all men, keep me upright and ſincere in that truſt that is recommended to my care: ſuffer me not to be drawn aſide with covetous luſt, nor to be carried away with the torrent of Prodigal expences: confine my thoughts within the bounds of Juſtice and Moderation, that I may give a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie account of my Stewardſhip, and prove juſt and innocent before God and man: Let not oppreſſion againſt the Orphans crie againſt me, nor unrighteous dealing corrupt my conſcience: If riches encreaſe, let not my heart be ſet upon them, but give me grace to keep Innocencie, and to do the thing that is right, that I may obtain peace at the laſt. Theſe are the bleſſings I humbly crave, (moſt bleſſed Lord) for Jeſus Chriſts ſake our Saviour. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="orphans" type="prayer">
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:119587:71"/>
                     <head>The Wards or Orphans Prayer.</head>
                     <p>MOſt gracious God and merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Lord, who art pleaſed to be a husband to the Widow and a father to the Orphans, I beſeech thee to look with pitie and mercie upon me; comfort me in the time of trouble, and relieve me in all diſtreſs. Provide me food and Rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, let thy goodneſs be my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, ond thy Prudence my Store<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe; help me to the benefit of a civil and Chriſtian Education, that I may in ſome degrees, grow in favour with God and man, let not my converſation be corrupted with Vice, nor my ſoul poiſon'd with ſin: Beautifie my Reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons with humilitie, contentedneſs and Obedience, that I may be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervant under Tutors and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours untill the time appointed; Encreaſe my faith in thee, O Lord, and make me ever to depend on
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:119587:72"/>thy mercie: And ſo ſeaſon my younger yeares with grace, that all my daies may be bleſſed and acceptable in thy ſight, through Jeſus Chriſt my bleſſed Saviour. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="tutours" type="prayer">
                     <head>The Tutours Prayer.</head>
                     <p>OEternal and Immortal Lord, who art Wiſdom, Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Sanctification and Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Enlighten my Underſtanding with the bright beams of thy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, Rectifie my Judgement and preſerve it from Errour, let not Schiſm, hereſie, or Atheiſm encline or direct my thoughts from the love of Truth, and ſo lead me by the grace of thy holy Spirit into the paths of Righteouſneſs, that I may be able to guide others to the Knowledge and love of Learning, and Wiſdom: And I humbly pray thee (bleſſed Lord) that holineſs
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:119587:72"/>may dwell ſo fully in my heart: that all my life I may be a good Example to others, and make thy glorious light ſo to ſhine before men, that in all things I may glorifie thy holy Name through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="scholars" type="prayer">
                     <head>The Pupils or Scholars Prayer.</head>
                     <p>MOſt gracious Father and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Lord, I do moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly confeſs that I am fearfully and wonderfully made, and that thou haſt preſerved me ever ſince I hanged about my mothers neck, be pleaſed ſtil to be propitious to me, to give me a wiſe Religious and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding heart, that I may the better learn to know and fear thy holy Name: Let not perverſneſs or frowardneſs interrupt my ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, nor Idleneſs benumbe, or childiſh wantonneſs diſperſe or
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:119587:73"/>ſtartle my affections from the love of Learning; keep me innocent from the Contagion of evil compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and let not lewd Examples in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect my tender Yeares, bend my heart with true obedience to my Teachers, and make me diligent and active in the performance of my Dutie: and ſo regulate the whole frame of my Converſation, that I may grow up as a young Plant, ſupported and propped with thy grace, that in due time I may prove a poliſhed corner of thy Temple, for Jeſus Chriſt's ſake. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="husbands" type="prayer">
                     <head>The Husbands Prayer.</head>
                     <p>MOſt mercifull Lord, who haſt admitted me to the holy ſtate of Matrimony inſtituted in Paradiſe; give me thy heavenly grace to live Reverently, diſcreet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, adviſedly, ſoberly, and in the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:119587:73"/>fear of God in that holy Ordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; Command my affections and guide them that I may love my wife, as my own bodie, my fleſh, and my bone; and as Chriſt loved his Church and gave himſelf for it. Suffer not any Root of bitterneſs to ſpring from my heart, nor to ſpread in my looks or language, or in any action towards my beloved, but let me ſo live in love with her and dwell to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in honour, knowledge, and the fear of the Lord, that we may be heires together of the grace of life, and that our prayers may not be hindred: and ſo enjoying the comfort of a holy life on earth, I may in the End obtain Eternal life in Heaven, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="wifes" type="prayer">
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:119587:74"/>
                     <head>The Wife's Prayer.</head>
                     <p>ALmighty Lord, who knoweſt beſt how to diſpoſe of thy ſervants and Handmaids: Aſſiſt me with thy grace and favour, that being joined in the holy ſtate of Matrimome, I may preſerve it Honourable and Undefiled, keep my heart in an humble ſubmiſſion to my husband as being my head, ſo that I may render him Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence honour and Obedience, make my Converſation to be chaſt cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled with the fear of God, my life innocent and inoffenſive, and my ſpirit mild and quiet, ſo that if any obey not the Word, he may be wonne without the word, by the converſation of his Wife. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect me (O Lord) from all Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations of evil Inclinations, and preſerve me from the motions, looks, and Inticements of lewd and wicked companie; let modeſtie
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:119587:74"/>ever appear in my looks, and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitie dwell in my Thoughts, that I may be a comfort and delight to my husband, and in all my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation an Example of grace and Vertue: All this I humbly beg for Chriſt Jeſus ſake my Saviour and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="widowes" type="prayer">
                     <head>The Widowes Prayer.</head>
                     <p>O God, who art Juſt in all thy works, and holy in all thy wayes; look on me thy poor ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant with the tender eye of pitie and mercie: Comfort me in my ſad and ſolitarie condition; be my head and Husband, to direct me in all my troubles: Protect me with thy Power; refreſh me with thy Favour, Counſel me with thy Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and be my Refuge in all dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and extremities; Let not Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and oppreſſion Injure my In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent weakneſs, nor any wanton
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:119587:75"/>Thoughts ſurpriſe me; preſerve me from the Attempts of laſcivious approaches: and let chaſt and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt Reſolutions keep me company: defend me from the Rage and fury of Ungodly and Unreaſonable men, give me grace to dedicate my ſelf both in ſoul and bodie to thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; And ſo to continue in thy favour and Protection, that my life may have comfort, and my End may be truly happie through Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="virgins" type="prayer">
                     <head>The Virgins Prayer.</head>
                     <p>HOlie, Holie, Holie, Lord God of Hoſts: who dwelleſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Cherubims, and whoſe eies cannot but with diſpleaſure, look on any thing that is Impure, preſerve me in thy Faith and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, that I may glorifie thee in bodie and ſoul, keep my eies from vain Objects, and my Eares from
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:119587:75"/>wanton diſcourſe; let not my ſenſes be ſurpriſed, nor my Reaſon cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivated with any luſtfull inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: Purifie my heart from all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs, and defend and keep me from the wiles and aſſaults of the World, the fleſh and the Devil: let my choiſeſt delight be fixed in the honour and ſervice of my God; And let my Affections be ſet chiefly on thoſe things which are above, where Chriſt ſits at the right hand of God; Let Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe and Charitie beautifie my Converſation; and let me be a Companion to thoſe who lead a godly life, that thy Name may be glorified, and my body and ſoul in the End Eternally ſaved through Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="jaylors" type="prayer">
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:119587:76"/>
                     <head>The Jaylors Prayer.</head>
                     <p>ALmightie Lord, who art the Creator of Heaven and Earth, be pleaſed to touch my heart with a true fear and Reverence of thy Holy Name; let not Aſperitie or fierceneſſe raiſe a tempeſt in my ſoul, but give me grace that I may perform the Dutie of my place, with fidelitie and a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, let neither the power nor the Treacherie of thoſe, who are committed to my Cuſtodie, be able to do me any injurie; Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort with pitie, and relieve with mercie all who are innocent, and graciouſly deliver <hi>Joſeph</hi> out of all his afflictions: ſhew him mercy and give him favour, Help thoſe that are indebted to their Libertie, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining their Creditors to pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and pitie, and ſo relieve them out of thine abundant ſtore, that they may owe nothing to
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:119587:76"/>any man but Love: As to Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors and Offenders, Lord give them penitent and relenting hearts, that the Lawes being ſatisfied, and Vice puniſhed, thy Name may be feared, Offenders terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and their ſoules ſaved: And let thy Grace and Goodneſſe ſo ſeaſon my ſoul, that I may as well Treat the Innocent with mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and kindneſſe as Command the moſt miſchievous, with Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and Prudence; I Lord hear my prayers, and let my Cry come unto thee, for Jeſus Chriſts ſake my only Lord and Saviour. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="innocent prisoners" type="prayer">
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:119587:77"/>
                     <head>The innocent priſoners Prayer.</head>
                     <p>O Lord, in whom we live, move and have our being; from whom we derive both health and happineſſe, receive my ſighes and groanes: Conſider my Tears, hear my Prayers, and have pitie on me, who am faſt bound in mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie an Iron: Suffer not a dark Dungeon to be my chamber, nor the cold ſtones my Couch: Let not Hunger, Thirſt and nakedneſs devour me, nor Lice and naſtineſs deſtroy me; Suffer not the ſtocks or ſhackles to hurt my hands, legs or feet, nor the Iron to enter into my ſoul. O look graciouſly on my innocencie; Preſerve me conſtant and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in true Zeal and love to thy Church; Strengthen my Loyaltie and Reſolutions of faith and true Allegiance towards my King; And whileſt it pleaſeth thee (O
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:119587:77"/>God) to make triall of me: let not any earthly torments afright me from my true love to thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; Make my face to ſhine with chearfulneſſe, as thou didſt Saint <hi>Stevens;</hi> Amidſt my greateſt trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, if it be thy good pleaſure de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver me out of miſerie, and from the hands of all my Enemies: if not (bleſſed Lord) thy Will be done: let not crueltie tire my pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, nor any earthly Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage ſo corrupt my Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, but that I may continue faithfull to the death, ſo that in the End, I may receive the Crown of life through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="malefactors" type="prayer">
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:119587:78"/>
                     <head>The Malefactors prayer in priſon.</head>
                     <p>O God, to whom Juſtice, and Vengeance belongeth: I beſeech thee, let not thy Wrath or diſpleaſure further fall upon me, but have mercy on me and that right ſoon; for now I am come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to great miſerie; my ſinnes have laid hold on me long ſince, and now thy Juſtice hath found me out. I have offended, and now am pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, abuſed my Libertie, and therefore am Impriſoned: (O Lord) waſh me from my ſinnes, and cleanſe me from mine iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Though they be Crimſon and Scarlet ſinnes, yet be pleaſed to pardon and forgive them all. Give me grace to look on my ſinnes as the cauſes and provocations of thy Judgements: and to conſider my tranſgreſſions as the only occaſions of my ſhame and ſorrow: make
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:119587:78"/>my ſtony heart to relent, and to guſh out with ſtreames of teares: that I have ſo offended God and man. Strengthen my faith in my Saviour Jeſus, and ſave my ſoul for his precious Merits ſake: let not hardneſſe of heart, and Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitencie bewitch, or benumme my ſoul, but have mercie upon me, and (if it be thy good pleaſure) that I muſt die for my offences to ſatisfie thy Juſtice; Righteous Lord, be pleaſed that my ſufferings and example may deterr all others from ſuch notorious crimes, and let my poor ſoul be Eternally ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, through thy great mercies in Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="exiles" type="prayer">
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:119587:79"/>
                     <head>The Exiles prayer.</head>
                     <p>ALmighty God, who for my ſinnes haſt forced me to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake my Countrey, and Kindred, and my Fathers houſe; give me grace to poſſeſs my ſoul in pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, to ſubmit chearfully to thy heavenly Will, and ever to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend on thy mercie and goodneſs; let not the ſinnes of ſtrangers en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice me, nor their Errours enſnare me to any wickedneſs; keep me ſound and firm in the true Faith of Chriſt, and ſuffer not ſubtile delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions to Infatuate my ſoul, nor evil Examples to corrupt my manners. Preſerve me from the poiſon of Schiſm, Hereſie, Atheiſm &amp; Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie; let thy Truth be my Guide, and thy Mercie my Protection; let holy and humble Reſolutions to depend on thy Favour comfort me in my di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs: and in good time, If it be thy bleſſed Will, O Lord, deliver
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:119587:79"/>me from baniſhment and reſtore me to my own Countrey, that I may yet live to praiſe thee in the great Congregation, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="captives" type="prayer">
                     <head>The Captives prayer.</head>
                     <p>O Moſt Juſt and Righteous Lord; It hath pleaſed thee to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer me to fall into the hand of cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el barbarous and bloody people, who deny my bleſſed Saviour Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, and deſpiſe the Holie Goſpel the Word of Life; I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly beſeech thee (moſt gracious Father) to behold my ſad condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with a tender Eye of ſweet compaſſion; and to ſtrengthen my faith in all trials of my Enemies; let neither the cruelty of men or Devil, or any elſe be able to ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate me from the love of God which is in Chriſt Jeſus our Lord. Give
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:119587:80"/>me courage to reſiſt all perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and force, that might Invade or remove my Reſolutions from thy Truth; let thy honour be my ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and the Name of my Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour Jeſus my Joy and comfort in all aſſaults and troubles: keep me conſtant and faithful to thy ſervice in my greateſt extremities, and make me to rejoyce in the croſs of Chriſt: And not to be terrified or aſhamed, bearing about me the marks of our Lord Jeſus: Grant me (Lord) a ſpeedie and happie deliverance out of my Enemies hands: If it be otherwiſe determin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, whether I die or live, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever I do or ſuffer, God give me grace to glorifie his holy Name, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="poor beggers" type="prayer">
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:119587:80"/>
                     <head>The poor beggers prayer.</head>
                     <p>MOſt ſweet and bleſſed Lord: who art the light of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and the comfort of all who are in diſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eſs and miſerie: look merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully on my ſad and low condition, who am cloathed with Rags, and pinch'd with povertie, which like an Armed man is ready to ſeize upon me: Remember thine Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed goodneſs (gracious Lord) and ſupply my neceſſities with thine Abundant Kindneſs; ſweeten my ſufferings with heavenly ſupplies: and let not hunger and thirſt, cold, and nakedneſs Utterly Devour me, Mollifie the hard hearts of thoſe who behold my miſerie, that they may have compaſſion towards me: and thou (O Lord) who makeſt the Lillies to grow, and feedeſt Ravens and Fowles of the Ayre; Provide food and Raiment for thy poor ſervant, and for thy mercies
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:119587:81"/>ſake Ranſom and redeem me from my ſad extremities: An yet if it pleaſe thee to make further trial of my patience and ſubmiſſion, (Lord) grant me a contented heart. And though I continue poor and needie, yet make me rich in the gifts and graces of thy holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that though I find no compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion at rich mens doores, yet when I die, I may (as <hi>Lazarus</hi>) be carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Angels into <hi>Abraham's</hi> boſome, for Jeſus Chriſt his ſake.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="seamans" type="prayer">
                     <head>The Seamans prayer.</head>
                     <p>O Almightie and Everlaſting Lord God, Thou giveſt us leave to go down to the Sea in Ships, and to have our buſineſs in great Waters, to behold the Works of the Lord, and to ſee the Wonders in the Deep. Preſerve
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:119587:81"/>us when the ſtormie wind Ariſeth: and lifteth up the loftie Waves: let not our ſoules melt with trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, when we are carried up to the Heaven or down again to the Deep; Though we Reel to all fro and ſtagger like Drunken men, and be at our wits end: yet, hear us graciouſly when we cry unto thee (O Lord) in our trouble, and deliver us out of our Diſtreſs; make the ſtorm to ceaſe, that the proud Waves may be ſtill and calm, Deliver us both day and night from the dangers of the deep, and ſuffer neither Pirats nor theeves nor any of our Enemies, to terrifie or take, or hurt us, to damage our ſhip or ſpoil our goods. Let our Voyage be proſperous, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours ſucceſsfull, and in the end, make us glad (O Lord) that we may be at reſt: And bring us to the Haven where we would be, that we may praiſe the Lord for his goodneſs and declare the Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders that he doth for the children
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:119587:82"/>of men, that his Name may be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver exalted, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="midwives" type="prayer">
                     <head>The Midwives prayer.</head>
                     <p>O Lord Eternal and Almighty, who commandeſt all thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to be uſefull &amp; helpful one to another, be pleas'd to give me both skill and Courage to aſſiſt and help thy Handmaid in her la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and travail: let not my hands or heart fail at her approaching danger, make my endeavours hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py and ſucceſsfull, and graciouſly anſwer the requeſts and deſires of thy humble ſervant, who now earn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtly prayeth for thy Bleſſing: let this Handmaid have eaſe and comfort in her greateſt pangs and ſorrows, that ſo by thy Providence and Goodneſs, being delivered from death and danger, ſhe may be
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:119587:82"/>made a joyfull Mother by the fruit of her Womb and birth of her Child. Grant Lord that the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant may be receiv'd into the world with comfort, and made thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant by Adoption and Grace, Through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="womans in labour" type="prayer">
                     <head>The Womans prayer in her la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and travail.</head>
                     <p>ALmightie and moſt graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous God; I know and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that ſtrength and weakneſs, danger and deliverance, life and death are in thy hands: I beſeech thee earneſtly for Chriſt Jeſus ſake, to comfort me in this time of trial that is now at hand: forgive my ſinnes which have cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed my ſorrowes, Mitigate and aſſwage my pain and pangs, and though I approach near the doors
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:119587:83"/>of death, yet recover me again, and ſuffer me not to faint or pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh in ſo great a danger: ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then my faith and patience, and give me happy deliverance of the fruit of my Womb: And graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly convert all my ſorrowes into Joy. O let my life be precious in thy ſight, that my preſervation e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver may oblige me to ſet forth thy praiſe and glory through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="aged persons" type="prayer">
                     <head>The Aged perſons prayer.</head>
                     <p>O Immortal and Almightie God, who art Eternity and the Ancient of daies; be propitious and merciful to me thy Aged ſervant; Though my face be furrowed and wrinckled, yet be pleaſed to Renew thy graces dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in me, and let thy holy Spirit breath afreſh the gales of thy Love and Favour on my ſoul, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake me not in my old Age (O
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:119587:83"/>Lord) (ſeeing the evil dayes are come upon me, and the yeares wherein I take no pleaſure, Though the Sun grow dark and my Eyes dimme, the keepers of the houſe tremble, the ſtrong men bow them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, the grinders ceaſe, and all the frame of my feeble body be terrified and ſhaken, yet forſake me not (moſt gracious Lord) in my old age; guide and keep me in the paths of Righteouſneſs to the end of my dayes: let no of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive Diſeaſes overtake me, nor my former ſinnes find me out to detect me, or Accuſe me, and ſuffer not the frailties and Errours of my youth now to ſeize on my fainting ſpirits, but let thy grace and goodneſs be my comfort, and thy mercy and pity, my deliverance, from my ſinnes, and thy diſpleaſure: that I may End and conſummate the few daies of my Pilgrimage in love, Joy and Peace both with God and man, though Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="young mans" type="prayer">
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:119587:84"/>
                     <head>The young mans prayer.</head>
                     <p>BLeſſed, holy, and Righteous Lord; Teach me to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber my Creator in the daies of my youth, and train me in the pathes wherein I ought to go, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer me not to walk in the counſel of the Ungodly, to ſtand in the wayes of ſinners, or to ſit in the ſeat of the ſcornful: direct me how I may ſo cleanſe my wayes, that I may take heed thereto ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to thy Word. Give me grace to ſeek thee with my whole heart, that I may not wander from thy Commandements: make thy Word the Treaſure of my ſoul, ſo that I may not ſin againſt thee. Allay all hot and unruly paſſions with the dew of thy grace: ſow the ſeeds of Vertue in the garden of my ſoul, and Weed out of my heart all Inclinations to Vice and ſin; keep me zealous to the love
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:119587:84"/>and duty of thy Lawes, and make me to ſtand in awe, and to be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid, more of diſpleaſing thee then of all the world beſides: Let not my heart be tempted with evil thoughts, or the wicked devices of men or Devils, nor my life corrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and debauched with lewd and ungodly companie. Give me grace (O Lord) to keep my lips from guile, and my Tongue from cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, lying, ſwearing and all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneſs: let my body be a Recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacle and Temple for the holy Ghoſt to dwell in, and my ſoul ſo filled with thy grace and heavenly Benedicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: that in the End both may be eternally ſaved, through the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of thy bleſſed Son, my bleſſed Saviour Jeſus. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="fathers" type="prayer">
                     <pb n="38" facs="tcp:119587:85"/>
                     <head>The Fathers prayer.</head>
                     <p>O Moſt glorious God and gracious Father in Jeſus Chriſt our Lord; let thy goodneſs and tender compaſſion en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline thy Eares to my prayers and ſupplications: Teach my heart to belive in thee, and to love, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and fear thee above all things: make me a holy and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Example of Pietie, Truth, Righteouſneſſe and goodneſſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my Children, whom thou haſt given me: Let all my thoughts words and deeds ſavour of Grace and Vertue; let thy holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements be my path to walk in: Thy Word my light and Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorn to guide me? Thy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments my Refection and comfort, Thy ſtrength my ſtay, Thy Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:119587:85"/>my Refuge: A good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience my Cordial, and thy praiſe and glory my chiefeſt End and aime: cloath me with Innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, Truth and uprightneſſe: and ſo adorn me with thy Grace and Goodneſſe, that I may bring up my children in the true faith and fear of God, that I and they may in the End prove Heires of Salvation through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord thy beſſed Sonne, O Lord; and our Saviour Jeſus. So be it.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="mothers" type="prayer">
                     <pb n="40" facs="tcp:119587:86"/>
                     <head>The Mothers Prayer.</head>
                     <p>O Lord Holy and Righteous, be gracious and propiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to me thy humble ſervant; and thou who dwelleſt in Heaven above; Conſider and hearken to the devout prayers of thy Handmaid. As thou haſt made me a Mother, ſo make me a grave and modeſt Matron; an Example of Holineſſe and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, in word and deed, to my Children: let it be my chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt care to breed and bring them up, bleſſed Lord, in thy Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, that cleaving faſt to thy Law even from their tender years, they may never fail in their Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty towards God or man, nor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from it; Continue me ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and compaſſionate to my chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:119587:86"/>and let not pride, cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe, filthy luſts or World<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Vanities withdraw or divert my true love from them: make my children my delight and O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live Branches round about my Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, whiles they are young: And when they grow into riper age, make them the ſtay and comfort of my Age, and give me and mine thy holy Grace (O Lord) that we may ever love and ſerve thee, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="childes" type="prayer">
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:119587:87"/>
                     <head>The Childes Prayer.</head>
                     <p>A Lmightie God and loving Father, who haſt Grace and mercy for all thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, who have pity and kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for themſelves. Continue thy goodneſſe and preſervation over me, that I may believe in thee, and fear, honour and love thee, with all my heart, with all my mind and with all my ſoul: make me Zealous in thy Worſhip and thankfull for thy mercies, and to ſerve thee truly and faithfully all the daies of my life. Teach me, (O Lord) to love my Neighbour as my ſelf, and give me a Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der heart devoutly to love, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour ond ſuccour my Father and Mother: A Loyal heart to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and obey my King and his
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:119587:87"/>Miniſters, an humble heart to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit my ſelf to all my Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, Teachers, ſpiritual Paſtors, and Maſters: ſo Guide and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern (bleſſed Lord) my whole life both in body and ſoul, that in my younger and riper yeares, in my youth and age, I may enjoy the comfort of thy holy Spirit, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="martyrs" type="prayer">
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:119587:88"/>
                     <head>An Innocent Martyrs prayer, or, a Loyal ſubjects prayer dying for a good Cauſe.</head>
                     <p>O Lord, who knoweſt the thoughts of all mens hearts, and diſcerneſt the ſecrets of the ſoul, be my guide and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in my Reſolutions, and let my love to thy Truth be the only Load<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone of my affections in this great Trial of my Chriſtian Faith and patience: let not the terrour nor torments of cruel men, not any temptations of Satan, divert my thoughts from thy ſervice; And whether I ſhall die or live, and end my daies by a violent or a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural diſſolution, Give me grace ſtill to put my truſt in thy mercy,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:119587:88"/>and to be true and faithful to the death: ſuffer me not to be aſhamed of my chain; nor diſcouraged with harſh unmercifull uſage, and aſad and cold Imptiſonment. Though I be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of competent food and Rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, threamed with death and haled to execution: yet be pleaſed (gracious Lord) to be my help and Refuge in all my miſerie. And ſo ſtrengthen my faith and affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in thy mercie and goodneſſe, that I may not be afraid of the flame of fire or faggot, nor be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maied at the ſharpneſs of the Ax or Sword, and though my gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments be rouled in blood, yet let the glorie of a righteous and good cauſe invite and oblige my Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to conſtancie and perſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, ſo that I may not be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med or afrighted, though I be forced by bloody minded men to a Halter or a Gibbet, make me able by an innocent life, and a Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Death, to convert my very E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:119587:89"/>nemies, as the noble Armie of Martyrs, and to be a faithfull wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of thy Truth. In my greateſt Agonie and Trial, give me grace to remember thoſe great Worthies, who for their Saviours ſake were ſtoned, were ſawen aſunder, and were ſlain with the ſword: or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, give me grace to look on my bleſſed Saviour; who, for the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry that was ſet before him, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed the ſhame, endured the croſs, and is now ſet down at the right hand of God; and, if I muſt ſuffer and die, ſo it be for a good cauſe and a good conſcience, The Lords holie Name be bleſſed, who for this light Affliction which laſteth but for a moment, will reward his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants with a Crown and weight of Eternal Glorie, which was pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="travailers" type="prayer">
                     <pb n="47" facs="tcp:119587:89"/>
                     <head>The Travailers prayer.</head>
                     <p>MOſt bleſſed Lord, who art the Protector of Heaven, and earth, and of all thy Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, look graciouſly upon me thy humble ſervant, Defent and keep me in my Journey: bleſs my go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cut and my coming in, be with me at my riſing up, and at my down-ſitting. Go with me and preſerve me whileſt I am in the way, and ſuccour and ſupply me with food and Raiment: com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort me when I am weary with reſt and refreſhment, and let me abide under the ſhadow of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie, that I may be defended under his Wings; and ſafe under his Feathers: ſo that the terrours of the night may be makee me afaid, nor the Arrow that flieth by day come near to hurt me:
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:119587:90"/>Suppreſs the Violence of wicked and ungodly men, that they may not have any power to do me hurt or injurie. And then (moſt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious God) who haſt ſuch a ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der care of the ſtranger, the Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, and the Orphan: Bleſs and proſper me in my Journe, as thou didſt <hi>Iſaac's</hi> ſervant. O let me not fall into the hands of Thieves and Robbers, as the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happie Travailer, who paſſed from <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to <hi>Jericho:</hi> nor to be inſna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red or ſurpriſed with the force or craft of cruel, deceitfull and miſchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous-minded men: Suffer me not to be ſtripped of my garments, nor maimed or wounded in my body, but be pleaſed to give thy holy An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels charge over me, to keep me in all my wayes. And ſo to bear me in their hands, that I may not ſo much as daſh my foot againſt a ſtone; Continue to me the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of Health and ſtrength, Peace and Libertie. And ſo proſper my
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:119587:90"/>travail and endeavours, that I may go out and Return both in thy fear and favour, and ſo receiving a good ſucceſs in my Journey; may have ever cauſe to praiſe thy holie Name for the goodneſs and mercie which endureth for Ever, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="private morning" type="prayer">
                     <head>A private Morning Prayer.</head>
                     <p>ALmightie and moſt gracious Lord, who haſt detended me from all the terrours of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs this laſt night paſt, and haſt refreſhed my body and ſoul with the favour of ſweet fleep, Reſt and Repoſe: give me grace this day entirely to devote and dedicate my ſelf to thy honour and ſervice:
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:119587:91"/>Let the beames of thy goodneſs Radiate and ſhine upon me to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve the Clouds of Ignorance, and to diſpel and ſcatter from my heart the works of darkneſs, and all Inclinations to ſinne and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs: Keep me from this Day as the Apple of thine Eye, and ſuffer neither the World, the fleſh or the Devil to inſnare or entice me to any Evil: Set a watch be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the door of my lips, that they may neither Utter perverſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſneſs my eies to be the windowes of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niquitie, to delight in ſinne, or to ſtare after Vanitie. Keep my hands in innocencie, and reſtrain my feet that they may not be forward or ſwift to ſhed blood, or to Act any miſchief: Let not my Throat be an open devouring Sepulchre, nor my Tongue defiled with cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, lying or ſwearing: but ſo bleſs me (O Lord God) in Through, word and deed, that I may like
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:119587:91"/>
                        <hi>Zechariah</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> be up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right and blameleſſe in my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation: I beſeech thee (Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venlie Father) to proſper me in that Station and Calling, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in thou haſt placed me, and make me a light to others by my good Examples. And ſo preſerve me by thy Mercie and Providence, that I may neither run into any ſinne, nor fall into any kind of danger. O let thy holie Angels by my Guardian, thy holie Word my Guide, and thy holie Spirit my Counſellour and Comforter. And ſo direct and inflame my Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that I may chiefly delight in Truth and Innocencie, that my whole converſation may be Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venlie, blameleſſe and inoffenſive; Let the fear of thy holie Name work ſo powerfullie on my ſoul, that I may never ſwerve or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viate from the paths of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, but walk on ſtill in them, that I may in the End obtain E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:119587:92"/>verlaſting life, though Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Amen-</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="private evening" type="prayer">
                     <head>A Private Evening Prayer.</head>
                     <p>O Eternal and Almightie Lord, who art the Watchman of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and whoſe Eies neither ſlum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber nor ſleep, be favourable and gracious, and continue thy Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and goodneſs towards me. As thou haſt bleſſed me this day paſt, ſo be pleaſed to receive me into thy gracious preſervation this Evening and night enſuing: for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give my ſinnes, that they may nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther provoke thy wrath or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure, nor terrifie or wound my conſcience; waſh my ſtained ſoul in the Crimſon blood of Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:119587:92"/>my Redeemer; Nail all my offences faſt to his meritorious Croſ, burie my iniquities in the Grave of his Humilitie; And ſo ſtrengthen may faith in Chriſt, that I may firmly believe that all my ſinnes are expiated, through the bitter death and Paſſion of my Lord and Saviour; from theſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward perſwaſions raiſe true com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts to my conſcience, and aſſiſt me with the Grace that I may not of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend thee, but Ever ſtudie and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to pleaſe thee (O my God) in Righteouſneſs and true Holineſs: In this humble con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence of thy future favour: (Lord) I recommend my ſoul and bodie unto thine Almightie Providence and Protection; Ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly beſeeching, that as I have received many Bleſſings and Tokens of thy Love this day: ſo I may this might be ſafe under the Wings of thy tender goodneſs. Preſerve me from the terrours of darkneſs, and
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:119587:93"/>ſuffer me neither to be aſſaulted, nor afrighted with any Evil; quiet my conſcience with the aſſurance of the forgiveneſs of my ſinnes, for my Saviours ſake; and let me not be ſcared with Dreames, nor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed with luſtful Thoughts: ſend me ſweet ſleep and repoſe, that being thereby refreſhed, I may be the better enabled to walk before God and man in my Vocation and calling: let not the hands of cruel men, nor any of thy Judgements ſurpriſe or overtake me, but let thy Power be my Defence and thy Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie my ſure Deliverance, that I may lie down and reſt in peace, and by thy favour riſe the next morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with joy and comfort: And all this I humbly beg for the glorie of thy Name, and for thy tender mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie in Jeſus Chriſt my bleſſed Lord and Saviour.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <q>
                        <hi>Our Father which art in Heaven,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
                  </div>
                  <div n="sick person" type="prayer">
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:119587:93"/>
                     <head>A private prayer for a ſick perſon.</head>
                     <p>ALmightie Lord, in whom we live, and move, and have our being; look down from Heaven: Behold, viſit, and relieve me thy ſick ſervant; Let not my ſinnes encreaſe my ſorrowes, nor mine offences heighten thy diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure; Strengthen me in my greateſt infirmities, and fortifie my Reſolutions to bear with patience, whatever Load thou ſhalt pleaſe to lay upon me: O forſake me not when my ſtrength faileth me, and go not far from (O God) but in all my extremities make haſt corrected me with ſickneſs, and haſt brought great troubles and Adverſities upon me, leading
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:119587:94"/>me in thy diſpleaſure, even to the very gates of Death, yet be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed (Graelens Lord) to turn a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to refreſh me with thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and to bring me out of the Deep of all my ſorrowes. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort me yet on every ſide after thy ſharp chaſtiſements, and give me grace to make a holy Uſe of all thy fatherlie Viſitations. And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther my ſickneſſe comes upon me for the exerciſe of my patience, a Trial of my faith, or a corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction for my finnes: (Bleſſed God) grant that I may give an humble and a heartie ſubmiſſion to thy good Will and pleaſure; and nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vainly to deſpiſe thy correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, nor weakly to faint, being now rebuked by God himſelf, if it be thy heavenlie Will: Grant (O Lord) that I may recover my health and ſtrength again before I go from hence and be no more ſeen: if it be otherwiſe determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, whether it be for health or
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:119587:94"/>ſickneſſe, for life or Death, Gods Will be done, the Lords Name be praiſed. In the mean time (Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Lord) defend my ſould with the ſhield of Faith, Arm my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions with the ſword of the Spirit, and cover and comfort my heart and conſcience with the Breſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate of Righteouſneſs, that I may be the better able to reſiſt the Temptation of Satan, and the Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities of the World, and not to ſhrink or to be ſwallowed up in the Gulf of my own infirmities or carnal weakneſſe; (O Lord) make my bed in all my ſickneſſe, and comfort me in all my ſorrowes: diſcharge me from my diſeaſe, and reſtore me to health and ſtrength again if it be thy Will, that I may live to praiſe thy Holie Name, for thy great and ſweet me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and all this I humbly crave for Jeſus Chriſts ſake my only bleſſed Lord and Saviour.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="dying" type="prayer">
                     <pb n="58" facs="tcp:119587:95"/>
                     <head>A prayer for a ſick perſon dying and departing out of the World.</head>
                     <p>MOſt gracious and Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal God, with whom the ſoules and ſpirits of all the Saints departed in thy faith an fear do live Eternally, in Bliſs and Glorie; ſhew thy moſt Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der favour and mercie towards me, in this my greateſt Agonie and Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction; Behold now (O Lord) how my houſe is readie to fall, my Duſt and Aſhes are returning to the Grave; my fleſh trembleth; my Boyling blood is readie to cool; my Eies grow dimme, and the whole frame of ſtrength and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture failes; my Tale is Told, my Glaſs is run, and the hour of Death is nigh at hand; I beſeenh
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:119587:95"/>thee (bleſſed Lord) to comfort and aſſiſt me in this juncture of extremities, and inundation of ſorrowes: Inflame my heart with Charitie and love towards all the World: ſtrengthen my faith a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all Temptations: give me a ſure Hope an firm confidence in thy. Mercie and Goodneſs: conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue to me the Bleſſing of Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, conſtancie and perſeverance to the End: that when I am diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved and depart this life, my ſoul may be elevated to Everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Joyes in the companie of the bleſſed Angels: And that my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, being repoſed in a bed of clay until the day of Judgement, may then receive a happie and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Reſurrection. Let the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of my Thoughts be fixed on my Redeemer, and be Intirelie coeleſtiallie diſpoſed, that my paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage may be more certain, ſure, and eaſie towards Heaven. And being purged from all my ſins in the blood
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:119587:96"/>of Chriſt, I may follow the Holie Lamb of God, and wait on my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer in Everlaſting Happineſs. Give me grace and courage free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to part with the World, and all Tranſitorie Vanities, and whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to reſign and recommend my body and ſoul into thy hands, that ſo I may continue thy faithfull ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant and Soldier to my lives End: and having fought the fight and finiſhed my courſe, I may receive the Immortal Crown of Glorie, through Jeſus Chriſt my Lord and Saviour.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="schools" type="prayer">
                     <pb n="61" facs="tcp:119587:96"/>
                     <head>A Prayer for the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities and Schooles of Learning.</head>
                     <p>LOrd, who art the Author and giver of all good things, I beſeech thy fatherly mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, to be Ever favourable and Propitious to the two Univerſities, and to all other Schooles and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties of Learning and pious Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, in this Kingdom, and of all other his Majeſties Dominions: And as thou haſt ſtirred up the hearts of many Worthies to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Founders, and Benefactors of thoſe famous Seminaries and Seed-plots: ſo let their Names and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories be precious in the ſight of God and man, for their good and charitable works; make ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing generations to imitate, and to be in love with their Examples;
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:119587:97"/>that Learning and Languages with Arts and Sciences, and the true Religion and the fear of God, may every dae more and more proſper and flouriſh: Keep the Schooles of the Prophets from the Rapine &amp; Ruine of covetous hearts, and ſacrilegious hands; Cleanſe thoſe Fountaines and Well-ſprings of Life, from the commixture of Ignorance and Impietie. Let not Schiſm, Hereſie or Atheiſm, Lurk or ſhelter themſelves under the Roof of thoſe happie Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, nor Boaſtingly ſet up them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves againſt Unitie, Peace and Pietie (O Lord) let thoſe Lamps never want Oyl: but that they may ſhine brightly abroad to the diſpelling of Darkneſſe; the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing of Errour, and to the Defence and Maintenance of Gods true Religion and Vertue: Make them who are in power to be truly worthie, diligent and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:119587:97"/>to their truſt; and kindle the love of Wiſdom and Learning in the Affections of all the Sonnes of the Prophets: That the ſtreames of Knowledge plentifully flowing from thoſe pleaſant Fountaines: the whole Land may be refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the People inſtructed, the Church Edified, and God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie glorified in all things: Through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="church of england" type="prayer">
                     <head>A private prayer for the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>ALmighty God thou haſt caſt us out and ſcattered us abroad: Thou haſt been diſpleaſed at us: O turn to us again: And though thou haſt
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:119587:98"/>moved the Land, and divided it, yet be pleaſed to heal the ſores thereof, for it ſhaketh: though thou haſt ſhewed thy people heavy things, and given them a drink of deadly Wine: yet, at laſt, give a token to ſuch as fear thee, that they may triumph becauſe of the Truth; be pleaſed (Gracious Lord) to be ever a help in the time of trouble, bleſs the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Church of Chriſt. And more eſpecially the Church of <hi>England;</hi> which like a Dove before the birds of prey, and a Lilly amidſt the Thornes, is inviron'd on every ſide with mortal Enemies. Continue this Church A pillar of Truth; and a Mother of many Bleſſings to all her children. Preſerve her in Doctrine and Diſcipline, that ſhe may keep the Unitie of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in the bond of Peace, in the Right Diſpenſation of thy Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Word, and in the bleſſed Uſe and Adminiſtration of thy holie
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:119587:98"/>Sacraments. Let not ſacrilegious hands make a prey of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches Patrimonie: Nor covetous minds Rob her of her Revenues: Suffer not the wicked to take the Houſes of God into poſſeſſion. But (O Lord) think upon thy Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation which thou haſt Redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and purchaſed of old: Think upon the Tribe of thine Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and of the Duſt of <hi>Sion:</hi> And let not them who have done ſuch Evils in thy Sanctuarie, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue any longer thy holy places to be Dennes of Thieves, or the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptacles of miſchief and propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. O let not heatheniſh mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men come into thine Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance to defile thy Holy Temple, or to make <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> an heap of ſtones. Suffer not the men of Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence to ſmite down thy people, or to trouble thine Heritage, to murder the Widow, or the Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, or to put the Fatherleſſe to Death, nor to ſhed the blood of
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:119587:99"/>thy ſervants, like water on every ſide of <hi>Jeruſalem:</hi> But (O Lord) As thou haſt been our Refuge from one generation to Another, ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come gracious to the Land: as thou haſt turned away the Captivity, ſo forgive the offences of thy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and cover their ſinnes, that they may ſtill rejoyce in thy Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Send (Bleſſed Lord) into this Church faithfull and holy Biſhops, Paſtors and Curates, that they may both by their life and Doctrine ſet forth thy true and holy Word, and rightly and duly adminiſter thy holy Sacraments to the glory of thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Name, and the Churches peace, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="for soveraign" type="prayer">
                     <pb n="67" facs="tcp:119587:99"/>
                     <head>A Subjects private prayer for his Soveraign.</head>
                     <p>O Lord, who haſt wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully delivered our Dread Soveraign ever ſince he was born: And after many Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als and Dangers, haſt reſtored him to his Royal Throne and Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; I earneſtly beſeech thee (mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull God) ſtill to be Gracious and Propitious to thine Anointed, and as thou haſt made his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to ſhout with joyfull Acclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions for the Kings return, ſo let him dwell ſecurely in their hearts and dutifull Affections. Preſerve his Royal Perſon from all perill and danger: Endue him with the overflowing Graces of thy Holy Spirit, and Adorn his ſoul with Vertue and goodneſs, that he may have a long, happy, peaceable and
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:119587:100"/>Proſperous Reign to the joy and comfort of all his Loyal Subjects: and to the terrour and Amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all his Enemies. And when it ſhall pleaſe thee (O Lord) that he ſhall ceaſe to Reign on Earth; Give him a Crown of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Eternal life which ſhall laſt for ever and ever, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="for royals" type="prayer">
                     <head>A Subjects private prayer for the Queen-Mother, the Duke of <hi>York,</hi> and the Royal Progeny.</head>
                     <p>MOſt gracious Lord, who haſt made three Kingdomes hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, by the encreaſe of a Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Off-ſpring: be pleaſed to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue thy mercy and favours to <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the Queen-Mother; to <hi>James</hi> Duke of <hi>York,</hi> and to all the bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:119587:100"/>of that Princely Progeny; let their perſons be ever precious in thy ſight: Prevent them all with the Bleſſings of thy goodneſs, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs them about with Songs of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance after their many ſorrowes. Let peace and plenty be their dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Attentants: and let their Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour be Great in thy Salvation; Give them many happy dayes on Earth, and in the End Crown them all with Eternal Glory, for Jeſus Chriſts ſake our Lord and Saviour.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epigraph">
                     <q>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. <bibl>1 Tim. 1.17.</bibl>
                     </q>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:119587:101"/>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="table_of_contents">
                  <pb facs="tcp:119587:101"/>
                  <head>The Contents.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1.</hi> THe Kings prayer. <hi>Page 1.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2.</hi> The Subjects prayer. <hi>p. 3</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>3</hi> The Captaines prayer. <hi>p. 4</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>4</hi> The Soldiers prayer. <hi>p. 6</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>5</hi> The Maſters prayer. <hi>p. 7</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>6</hi> The ſervants prayer. <hi>p. 8</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>7</hi> The Guardians prayer. <hi>p. 10</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>8</hi> The Wards prayer. <hi>p. 11</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>9</hi> The Tutors prayer. <hi>p. 12</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>10</hi> The Pupils prayer. <hi>p. 13</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>11</hi> The Husbands prayer. <hi>p. 14</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>12</hi> The Wifes prayer. <hi>p. 16</hi>
                     </item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:119587:102"/>
                     <item>
                        <hi>13</hi> The Widowes prayer. <hi>p. 17</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>14</hi> The Virgins prayer. <hi>p. 18</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>15</hi> The Jaylors prayer. <hi>p. 20</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>16</hi> The innocent priſoners prayer. <hi>p. 22</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>17</hi> The Malefactors prayer in priſon. <hi>p. 24</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>18</hi> The Exiles prayer. <hi>p. 26</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>19</hi> The Captives prayer. <hi>p. 27</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>20</hi> The beggers prayer. <hi>p. 29</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>21</hi> The Seamans prayer. <hi>p. 30</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>22</hi> The Midwives prayer. <hi>p. 32</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>23</hi> The woman in travails prayer. <hi>p. 33</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>24.</hi> The Aged perſons prayer. <hi>p. 34</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>25.</hi> The young mans prayer. <hi>p. 36</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>26.</hi> The Fathers prayer. <hi>p. 38</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>27.</hi> The Mothers prayer. <hi>p. 40</hi>
                     </item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:119587:102"/>
                     <item>
                        <hi>28.</hi> The Childes prayer. <hi>p. 42</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>29.</hi> An Innocent Martyrs Prayer. <hi>p. 44</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>30.</hi> The Travailers prayer. <hi>p. 47</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>31.</hi> A private Morning-prayers. <hi>p.49</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>32.</hi> A private Evening prayer <hi>p. 52</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>33.</hi> A private prayer for a ſick per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon <hi>p. 55</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>34.</hi> A prayer for a ſick perſon dying and departing out of the World. <hi>p. 58</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>35.</hi> A prayer for the Univerſities. <hi>p. 61</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>36.</hi> A private prayer for the Church of <hi>England. p. 63.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>37.</hi> A Subjects private prayer for his Soveraign. <hi>p. 67</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>38.</hi> A Subjects private prayer. <hi>p. 68</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
